<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bhashkar Sharma</title>
    <atom:link href="http://bhashkar.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>http://bhashkar.me</link>
    <description>Dreamer. Tinkerer.</description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 13:40:00 +0630</pubDate>
    <generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>Technology and Openness</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2015/03/04/technology-and-openness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 13:40:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2015/03/04/technology-and-openness/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The idealist in me wants to see the walled gardens of technology fail and fall.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The technologist in me is happy that at least people are getting a quality service &lt;del&gt;for free&lt;/del&gt; in exchange for their data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I would personally prefer Jabber to Hangouts or Facebook Messenger, but in the long run, it probably wouldn’t work on an Internet financed by data harvesting and advertisements. Where would you get the money to pay for servers? And then there is the question of maintaining and improving the product quality and user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a user I prefer the ease of dropping the files in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://dropbox.com&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; folder and not have to worry about syncing; or to be able to leave an offline message to my friends on one of the proprietary services and be assured that they will see it when they come online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a way to bring seamless UX and open technologies together, and whoever figures it out will revolutionize software in a big way. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ubuntu.com/&quot;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; is a great step in the direction, but we have a long way to go. I like BitTorrent initiatives towards launching user-friendly decentralized applications such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.getsync.com/&quot;&gt;Sync&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://labs.bittorrent.com/bleep/&quot;&gt;Bleep&lt;/a&gt;; the odds of them being used are a hundred times more than command-line tools, or self-hosted Jabber installations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I care about and love technology because it allows us to share our ideas with each other in a tangible form. The Internet has become successful because it makes it possible to reach people across the globe just by writing some lines of code and running it on a computer in my garage, or even in Amazon or Google’s garages. The power of technology is in making things easier for people, and enabling people to do things they previously couldn’t. Empowering people is the reason technology has become mainstream despite 99% of people not understanding how it works. And it is okay to an extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as there is oversight and laws protecting people’s interests, it is okay for common man to not understand how their machines work under the hood (although I always recommend learning more about things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem today is that both, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savetheinternet.com/net-neutrality-what-you-need-know-now&quot;&gt;companies&lt;/a&gt; and governments are trying to control the Internet and turn it from something that allows free flow of ideas, into a system that works in their own best interests. It is not inherently surprising, as humans have the ability to empathize only with a very small number of people whom they personally interact with. Others are relegated to account numbers or email addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/4VdO7LuoBzM?start=833&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system should be designed to be temper-proof from external agents like these that cripple its freedom. As it is, not every computer on the Internet is an equal citizen. A lot of that is on the whims on the ISPs, governments and technology providers. Heading further in this direction can only stifle the freedom that has brought about the free Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/fpbOEoRrHyU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for illegal activities such as child-porn and drug-trade happening online, there ought to be, and already are, laws that limit these activities. Every once in a while, there are crackdown on such activities. Unluckily, there is no vaccine for human nature and creativity when it comes to finding novel solutions and workarounds. After all, that is how we became civilized enough to reach here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people want to enjoy talking to their friends and watching cat videos on the Internet without having to worry about all the complexity that goes into its working. Their rights to privacy should be respected and protected. Despite plenty of wiretapping and snooping done by governments, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/nsa-phone-record-collection-does-little-to-prevent-terrorist-attacks-group-says/2014/01/12/8aa860aa-77dd-11e3-8963-b4b654bcc9b2_story.html&quot;&gt;White House-appointed group found out&lt;/a&gt; that it hadn’t lead to any effective stopping of terror activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you make fear the rationale behind making your laws, there is something inherently wrong and badly in need of a fix.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Christmas</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/12/25/christmas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2014 12:40:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/12/25/christmas/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Trying a simple painting today: &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://static.bhashkar.me/images/christmas.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self Help</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/11/20/self-help/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 11:00:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/11/20/self-help/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been a fan of self-help books in the past.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; I definitely have learned some things that help me live my life slightly better because of having read those books, but here’s the trick: most of the things that are mentioned in those books are rather obvious. They do have a fancy way of putting down the obvious, and a story or two in tow to aggrandize the effect. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being an utterly curious creature, I tend to ask myself questions which might sound strange or stupid to most. Almost every time such a question has sent me down a rabbit hole and helped me figure out a thing or two that I wasn’t previously aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point, that is what I thought I should take up as a profession - helping people figure out their lives. But as I have learned and grown; I’ve realized two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People don’t realize things unless they actively search for the answers themselves. You can’t spoonfeed them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s too much of show and shady stuff in this field. I would steer clear of becoming a part of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to mention that I am still trying to figure my own life out, and I don’t think that I qualify to “coach” others yet. I realize that life is a journey and the entire process is about figuring things out, learning from and enjoying the experiences, one day at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wish</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/11/09/wish/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2014 11:00:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/11/09/wish/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As long as Lisa can remember, they have had Bruno in their house.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Bruno is the German Shepherd that her parents brought home as a pup when she was 2. They practically grew up together, and became best buddies. They used to play, run, go for walks together. She would take care of feeding him. Sometimes they’d sit and eat next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lisa was now 9. She could swear that Bruno understood all of her commands. “Fetch”, “roll” and “play dead” didn’t even scratch the surface. He’d know when to go for a walk, and come running when called for dinner. Lisa wished there was a way she could understand what he had to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christmas was approaching and her parents were planning to get her a new bicycle for present. She had grown taller and her older bike now fell short, quite literally, for her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was Christmas eve. After having dinner and wishing everybody good night, Lisa went to bed. Before falling asleep, she made her wish. “Please make me able to understand what Bruno has to say”, she muttered with closed eyes and folded hands. And off to dreamland she went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next morning, Lisa woke up to see the Christmas tree finally decorated and lit up, and many boxes of presents underneath it. It might have one of the new video games she’s wanted. “Merry Christmas, honey”, said her mother. Suddenly Lisa remembered something. She started looking for Bruno. She called out his name, “Bruno!”. Maybe he’s still asleep. She started walking from room to room searching for her best friend. There he was, underneath the bed. “Bruno, wake up. It’s Christmas”, she said. “Na und? Ich bin nicht Christlich”, replied a gruff voice. Bruno turned his head and went back to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>At The Airport</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/11/04/at-the-airport/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 15:10:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/11/04/at-the-airport/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the midst of the hustle of the busy airport, he noticed how lonely he was.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The human brain is a wonderful thing. Even having people all around us can make us feel lonelier than when we are in true solitude on top of a mountain. People walking around with their trolleys, kids munching on to fast food and sipping cola from paper mugs, the shops all lit up, inviting people to come in and buy things they probably don’t need very much. The old people in the wheelchairs being dragged around by relatives or servants. Curious kids running around the lounge.
The airline staff talking around with their luggage. Just another workday for them, an emotional moment of separation for many. Many hopeful faces talking around, probably looking forward to their stint ahead in life, looking to get indulged in what lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So many colors, so many faces, so many forms. So different, yet connected somehow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Game Is On</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/07/05/the-game-is-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2014 21:40:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/07/05/the-game-is-on/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This one took a lot more time and effort than the previous one: &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://static.bhashkar.me/images/IMG_20140705_203640.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m feeling a little bad about the quality of the not-so-great paper I’m currently using. An upgrade is needed for heavy-duty stuff such as this one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iron Man</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/06/30/iron-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2014 09:10:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/06/30/iron-man/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Picked up the brush after 4 years, and painted this: &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://static.bhashkar.me/images/IMG_20140629_213859.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully will create more.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attachment</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/06/09/attachment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 21:10:40 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/06/09/attachment/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Someone said some rude things to me, which made me unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today it hit me that I wasn’t unhappy because what the words were; they were not true to begin with and I always knew that. I was unhappy because I did not expect that person to say those things to me.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not a revelation to me; in fact I might have imparted this wisdom on some poor soul at one time or the other. It is just that we all need reminders from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attachment makes people get to know and come close to each other. It also can result in pain if there is a mismatch of expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iCvmsMzlF7o&quot;&gt;allowing yourself to become vulnerable&lt;/a&gt; is an integral part of the process of getting close to someone, we should remind ourselves that it is a choice we make, and are at all times in full control of how we choose to react.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tagged</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/05/25/tagged/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 19:10:40 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/05/25/tagged/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The elections for the Indian Parliament have finished; and people are on their way to pick up another label they identify themselves with.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world run by corporations and branding, it is not surprising that everything has become a label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But are we going too far with this? People flaunt the brand of the clothing they wear, the gadgets they carry, the cars they drive. I suppose it is not inherently bad. But when it we start recognizing ourselves by the stuff we own, it might be the signs of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Labels used to be recognized for the values the organizations represented. In the PR age, looking and sounding cool has become more important than ever before. If you want to be identified in the age of information overload, you have to do things as a brand that show you as different from the others. This applies equally to corporations and persons who are brands. This is why everybody wants to be seen doing good things, regardless of whether it has any effect on the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Labeling is not limited to brands, though. We label ourselves and others with the schools we attend, the companies we work for, the country we belong to, the beliefs we follow and even the color of skin or gender. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we see people not as individuals but stereotype them as a member of a group whose population runs in thousands or millions; it is rather hard to have a sensible discussion of any kind. We can see this in action everywhere from the feminists, some of whom have taken the purpose of the movement to mean ‘hating all men’; to racism, caste or creed, geography or any other way we choose to discriminate with fellow humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the history of human civilization, every single war can likely be traced back to people acting crazy about some label or the other.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perversion</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/05/13/perversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 09:10:40 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/05/13/perversion/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across this beautiful video recently:&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/Z7dLU6fk9QY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook, the social network that makes the world more “open and connected”, has created new definitions for some words which have a deep connection with emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the word ‘Like’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;like (/lʌɪk/)
verb
1. find agreeable, enjoyable, or satisfactory.
synonyms:   be fond of, be attached to, have a soft spot for, have a fondness for, have a liking for, have regard for, think well of, look on with favour, hold in esteem, admire, respect, esteem;
antonyms:   dislike, hate
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have taken a subset of the possible meanings of the word, since it also can be used as a preposition, adverb or noun. We’re sticking to the verb usage for now. Let’s see what #2 has to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;like (/lʌɪk/)
verb
2. indicate one&amp;#39;s liking or approval of (a web page or posting on a social media website) by means of a particular icon or link.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wait? What? You’re telling me I use the same word to express my emotions; and to mention the action of clicking a button? I surely am not the only one who finds it strange, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words are the medium using which we express ourselves. If the words which are used to express the most human of feelings are “owned” by corporations, I feel that they lose their meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s another word integral to our culture that has fallen victim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;friend (/frɛnd/)
noun
1. a person with whom one has a bond of mutual affection, typically one exclusive of sexual or family relations.
synonyms:   companion, boon companion, bosom friend, best friend, close friend, intimate, confidante, confidant, familiar, soul mate, alter ego, second self, shadow, playmate, playfellow, classmate, schoolmate, workmate, ally, comrade, associate;
antonyms:   enemy
(used as a polite form of address or in ironic reference) an acquaintance or a stranger one comes across.
2. a familiar or helpful thing.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And then there is this meaning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;friend (/frɛnd/)
noun
3. a contact on a social networking website.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;‘Like’ has become so ambiguous that people now have the need to check which of the two likes I meant. It has happened to me more than once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recognize that language is an ever-evolving medium and it adapts to the cultural changes. I think we can do better than sacrifice etymology for profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a video on a related note. I have marked it to play at the relevant location, but I recommend watching the full video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/4VdO7LuoBzM?start=884&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Going Static</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/04/10/going-static/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 12:30:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/04/10/going-static/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After running the site on an EC2 machine for the last ~ 2 years, while simulaneously writing on various blogs (mostly because I was afraid of losing data); I’ve finally decided to go static.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured I wasn’t making use of the benefits of having a Linux box at my disposal; and what I was running could easily be run on a static host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I landed on &lt;a href=&quot;http://wintersmith.io&quot;&gt;Wintersmith&lt;/a&gt; after going through a couple of static site generators. It felt clean, simple and powerful enough for my requirements, so I figured I’d give it a shot. After importing my blog posts from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.bhashkar.me&quot;&gt;personal&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://rockerhome.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;technical&lt;/a&gt; blog, here we are. I’m planning to make the deployment process a bit easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I might have lost all the emails sent to my personal email address in the last few months because I didn’t set up the MX records in DNS settings; because I assumed &lt;a href=&quot;http://iwantmyname.com&quot;&gt;someone&lt;/a&gt; would take care of it. I didn’t bother checking since it is not my primary address and I rarely, if ever, use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The background image was clicked in Nainital in Nov’13 when I was visiting home for Deewali. You can find the link to the theme source at the bottom of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the code for this site &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bhashkarsharma/my-static-site&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canvas width and height</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/03/06/canvas-width-and-height/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2014 15:30:57 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/03/06/canvas-width-and-height/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When using canvas, remember to add width and height attributes to the markup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;tag&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;canvas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&quot;200&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;attribute&quot;&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;=&lt;span class=&quot;value&quot;&gt;&quot;300&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;tag&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;canvas&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;even if you have defined them in the CSS, otherwise you might see some unexpected code behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stunning Fail</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/03/01/stunning-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 12:27:43 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/03/01/stunning-fail/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloombergview.com/articles/2014-02-28/tesla-is-a-car-not-a-revolution&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;, many things come to mind; and not just how it screams “sensationalism” and “nay-sayer” out loud.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.bloomberg.com/image/iUVPBRrLZNPg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stunning, indeed!&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musk is headed for a “stunning fail” - Edward Niedermeyer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nostradamus takes a series of arguments, adds layers of “if this then that” on top, and tries to create a straw man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in my sleep I could smell oil on this article. Musk was a newcomer into the payments industry and he re-invented things with PayPal. SpaceX is the first private company in the world that has been able to successfully go farther than government agencies like NASA, and at a cheaper cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People said the idea that Tesla could begin shipping the Model S to customers in 2012 was absurd, that they were naive and didn’t understand the complexities of building a vehicle like Detroit does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before that, everyone said nobody would buy electric vehicles because (a) you can’t get them over 100 miles in range, and (b) because there is no charging infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would rather live in a world where a man like Musk is pushing the realm of possibilities to the next level as opposed to one in which he joins the rest of us hoping for some miracle to come out of the behemoth car (or any other) industry which hasn’t really done much to innovate in fields like energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it happens to be a “stunning fail”, it would be more glorious and would have changed the world more than most others in their entire lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facebook buys Whatsapp</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/02/20/facebook-buys-whatsapp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 14:43:29 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/02/20/facebook-buys-whatsapp/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;$19 billion. This is the amount of money Facebook is paying (stocks + cash + RSUs) to acquire WhatsApp. I’ve not been able to process it yet. Don’t get me wrong. I’m not questioning the worth of WhatsApp.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;It is a great messaging app which provides a simple, no-frills and reliable way of communicating with people, sharing images, videos, music etc. I have tried using a couple of other messaging apps and every time came back to WhatsApp. That is how good it is. And ~500 million customers without any marketing is a huge deal that speaks volumes for the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But something does not add up. Or maybe I’m too naive to understand it yet. WhatsApp supposedly deletes messages from their servers once they gets delivered. And they want nothing to do with advertising. Two things that Facebook is big on: data and advertising. Which leaves people’s contact list, which Facebook already has, in most cases by virtue of being installed on almost every Android/iOS phone out there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WhatsApp’s founder has &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.whatsapp.com/index.php/2014/02/facebook/&quot;&gt;promised&lt;/a&gt; to keep the product and services running as is, without ads. So what is Facebook really getting for $19B? WhatsApp has become the app which has almost entirely replaced SMS and other messaging services for most people I know (speaking for student and professional crowd in India). By becoming the de-facto communication standard of sorts, and being present on every mobile device with a data plan, they have disrupted mobile messaging. Add to it the ability to create groups, and you have a pretty solid product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to mention that you save a lot of money, which is probably why I would be willing pay $5 or even $10 instead of $1/year. I think the fact that it is a private social network with a deep reach (across multiple platforms including Symbian) is a big thing. Also, there is zero effort on the user’s part to get started, besides installing the app. You can choose to share content with one or many people, and you only see what people directly share with you. It keeps the noise away. This, in addition to absence of advertising, makes it a good experience for one-to-one or one-to-many interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it makes me think that this belittles the value of the hard sciences, medical and life saving research that people put their lives into. But then, Facebook was also valued at $100 billion+, right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amusing ourselves to death</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2014/01/08/amusing-ourselves-to-death/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2014 15:26:14 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2014/01/08/amusing-ourselves-to-death/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two prophecies. Neither came true; or both did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://onthepathofknowledge.wordpress.com/2014/01/03/amusing-ourselves-to-death/&quot;&gt;Read original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enough Arrangements!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/11/24/enough-arrangements/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2013 08:13:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/11/24/enough-arrangements/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m sick and tired of arranged marriages and the slew of shit they bring. Evils ranging from dowry to casteism to superstition like astrology are all prevalent in today’s India in a big way, thanks to this epidemic.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally know people who took decisions to please their parents or society and gave up on their love. I know people whose relationships didn’t culminate into marriage because of this sickness. I know people who lost touch with their families just because the person they married wasn’t right for them according to the thousand year old moronity doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are mostly dumb. They don’t use their brains, and only rely on others to approve of what they’re doing. These “others” are the people who have no clue about why things are the way they are, what morality or humanity means. They just are interested in imposing their beliefs on others. Beliefs which they themselves didn’t put any thought into. They just believed what they were told to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think, that as intelligent, educated and sensible individuals, we should do our part to put an end to this culture of blackmail and mental torture prevalent throughout our society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong. I have nothing against suggested alliances where parents suggest a suitable spouse to their child and then leave it to them to evaluate or decide what they want. My problem is with the model where these supposedly grown-up, educated and independent adults give in to the pointless notions of society and blackmail of their parents to choose the evil. In my opinion, parents should be glad that their children are mature enough to take their life decisions responsibly and are not dependent on them, instead of rallying them around telling them what to do throughout their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it’s all about power and ego (as with most other things where people are trying to control other people). Parents think that they’ll lose the control on their children if they allow them to marry who they want. Society thinks that people should all be sheep who are following the trend set by the herd. Religion obviously shows love marriages as wrong since they lose control over telling people who they should spend their lives with. And in case someone happens to choose a person with a different belief system, the babas stand to lose their customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arranged marriages are bullshit and I’ll be one of the happiest people on the planet if this travesty was abolished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an article published in ‘The Hindu’ on the topic: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/open-page/not-for-arranged-marriage/article5204945.ece&quot;&gt;Not for arranged marriage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Just Because</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/11/23/just-because/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2013 22:07:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/11/23/just-because/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I refuse to give up. I refuse to let the world turn me into a cynic. I refuse to stoop to the level of the people who see fellow humans as things to be used and discarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since always I have had faith in humanity; a quality which is hard to describe, but I will try. It is about caring, sharing and nurturing the people around you.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; It is about giving without thinking what you are getting in return. It is about being open to new ideas and experiences. It is about that feeling in your heart that might ‘restore your faith in humanity’. It is about the warmth that somebody makes you feel just by being there. It is about letting yourself be swept off your feet even though logic might suggest otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://qph.is.quoracdn.net/main-qimg-1bf11726154e8333d1a0b815388f35ac&quot; alt=&quot;The problem with getting attached&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there’s another side to it. After all, we are all just animals. Living creatures, who grow up in our surroundings, interact with others in the habitat we share and make decisions based on the experiences we have. Everyone we meet is fighting a battle. As sentient beings, it is not merely about survival. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow's_hierarchy_of_needs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Maslow described&lt;/a&gt;, it is about achieving various things in different stage of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/60/Maslow&amp;#39;s_Hierarchy_of_Needs.svg/450px-Maslow&amp;#39;s_Hierarchy_of_Needs.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;Maslow&amp;#39;s Hierarchy of Needs&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I think I probably should become more of what some people call, sigh, ‘practical’. As a rational and logical being I think I am practical. But this usage of the word is different. It is used to describe using someone for your purpose and moving on. My heart refuses to become that person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People were meant to be loved and things were meant to be used; instead we started loving things and using people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is only one thing in life that interests me: learning and exploring. I have no interest in the riches. I think that any individual living sensibly and working hard enough can gather a big house and car. But is that all what your life is worth? A house? A car? What really matters in life is what you make of it. How much do you affect others’ lives, how you make them feel, and whether you are able to make a difference, however minor it might be. At the end of it all, what matters is whether you will feel it was worth all that you put into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Reconsider your definitions. We are prone to judge success by the index of our salaries or the size of our automobiles rather than by the quality of our service and relationship to mankind.”
— Martin Luther King Jr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I recall reading, live a life where you leave the world a little better than you got it; even if it is just by making a small garden in your front yard.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Joys</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/10/11/small-joys/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 19:30:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/10/11/small-joys/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most of us are living life in the fast lane. A life which is more of a race than a journey. We are competing with each other to get ahead and reach somewhere. But where?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a moment and think of all that we have missed out on because of being in the race mindset.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love nature; listening to the sounds of birds chirping, water flowing, rain falling. I don’t remember the last time I was at a place so peaceful where I could listen to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love to take long strolls and jog on empty roads. I don’t get to see empty roads even at 1AM nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love to be near greenery. This is something I’m not entirely deprived of, thanks to the area that I live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t recall the last time I was able to lie down in the warm sun on a winter day and enjoy a nap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love to read, and write. I love to create new and beautiful stuff. I love to let my imagination fly. I love music. These are some things I am able to do, and I’m extremely grateful about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Slow down and smell the roses” is not just a phrase. It is an advice that we should heed to every once in a while by taking time out of our packed schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the omnipresent miniature computers that we carry around in our pockets, we have lost the touch of human connection; when ironically these devices were supposed to bring us closer, to make us more efficient so we can get more time to ourselves and those important to us. People sitting around a table having lunch are lost in their devices, forgetting the people in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have become zombies, screen junkies seeking attention from our online networks; while ignoring the human-ness of connecting with someone next to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s an amazing comic (click on the image to read):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zenpencils.com/comic/129-marc-maron-the-social-media-generation/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/LFdNa3R.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Social media generation&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is a series of moments, each following the other. If we postpone our happiness till a wish is fulfilled, we are limiting our happiness. Given the unpredictability of life, does it not make sense to be happy and grateful for what we have? Don’t get me wrong. I’m not talking about compromising and limiting ourselves. I’m talking about making the best of what we have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dream big and aim to achieve the best, work as hard as you can; but don’t keep your happiness locked away till you get what you want. Be happy about the smallest things, be it a baby smiling across the street or a tasty flavor of ice cream you recently discovered, or a mind-blowing song that you came across.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terminating the experiment</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/29/terminating-the-experiment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2013 06:30:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/29/terminating-the-experiment/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I started this experiment. The goal was to write a post everyday. I have to say I have failed miserably at keeping that goal up. I have barely been able to write 6 posts. But then, I guess it is not easy writing everyday especially when you have other things on hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will change this goal to be once a week (will aim for more frequently than that). A week is a reasonable amount of time to come up and compose a good write-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can’t express how let down I feel.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doing What We Dream Of</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/27/doing-what-we-dream-of/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2013 03:00:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/27/doing-what-we-dream-of/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As kids, we all dream of being someone when we grow up. It might be hard to believe, and maybe it was because of all the books I had around me when I was growing up; I wanted to write. That’s it. Spend time with books, read and write.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next thing I wanted to be, was a superhero. I guess that is a phase in every boy’s life when growing up. Superheroes are awesome. They’re perfect, powerful and can do whatever they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I entered this thing we call ‘the system’. I try to keep things interesting because most of the ‘normal’ things don’t make sense to me. I like doing things because there is a logical reason behind them, not because everyone else does it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I keep repeating like a parrot, Steve Jobs said some amazing things about doing what you love. The movie ‘Zindagi Na Milegi Dobara’ had similar tones of choosing happiness in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine recently shared this video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/jpe-LKn-4gM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, I was reminded of all the people who hate their work, and feel it doesn’t make a difference either. But they’re stuck in there just because.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is short. We should keep it exciting, amazing and interesting. Doing boring things sucks. You never know when you’re going to run out of the limited time you have on this planet. Choose to do things wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Food, Sleep and Exercise</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/24/food-sleep-and-exercise/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2013 14:30:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/24/food-sleep-and-exercise/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health is wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a proverb we are all too familiar with. And one most of us choose to disregard, until we lose our health.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our bodies are super complex machines. Like all machines, they need energy, rest, cleaning and regular usage to prevent what would be analogous to rusting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food should be healthy, properly prepared, clean and nutritious in order for the body to receive all the chemicals it needs to function smoothly. Till a few decades back, we were still figuring out the science in the foods and categorizing them into different buckets (vitamins, proteins, carbs, fats etc). There were cases of scurvy especially noticed in sailors. That’s what led to the discovery of Vitamin C. I’m not saying we have it all figured out already. There might be nutrients that we have yet to identify as essential for the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industrial revolution, green revolution and globalization have changed the scenario by turning it around. Today you can purchase fruits grown in foreign countries at your neighborhood store. This has led to huge number of choices presented to us like never before. At the same time, of the available choices, majority are unhealthy. Food containing carbs, oils and sugar without any nutritional value has been a big cause in the widespread endemic of obesity in the world today. And the choices amongst these are increasing by the dozen every day. One has to be very careful and not get lured by the fun-looking advertisements to make these decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sleep is extremely necessary for life. I remember reading that people can die from sleep deprivation faster than they can die of hunger. In the fast life where people spend hours daily traveling to and back from work, getting a good rest and sleep is almost a blessing. Cities are never silent, even in the night. There is always vehicular and horn noises disturbing the peace of the night. This can have a bad impact on sleeping patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exercise is as crucial for the body as food. Our bodies are designed to be physically active; while the office lifestyle requires us to sit for hours on a chair staring into the screen. This can cause problems in the long run. There was a study which stated that if you sit in front of a computer for more than 11 hours a day everyday, there is a 40% chance that you will die before 50. Since our work doesn’t require us to move, we should ensure that we do so on our own. Be it yoga, running or weight training, I think there should be some sort of physical health-based activity we should dedicate our daily time to, especially when living a fast life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Best Medicine</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/23/the-best-medicine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 18:00:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/23/the-best-medicine/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sense of humor has been linked to intelligence; and I’m not surprised. I don’t recall seeing a deer cracking up in the woods; but then I don’t frequent the woods. Bears scare me.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sobriety has its upsides, but only for a while. There’s a reason so many authors and creative people died of substance abuse - they found it preferable to the alternative. The addition of ethanol to blood causes many a hidden talents to show. There’s a reason “Hold my beer and watch!” is one of the most famous last words. Besides, no good story starts with “So I was eating salad…”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making people laugh is serious business. It is tough being funny. If comedy was easy, we would be living in a different world. Lately I have observed many a stand-up comics, and the ones I enjoy listening to the most are the ones who make us think. After listening to stupid jokes about bodily functions or mothers-in-law for years, it was a pleasant change to listen to comics who talk about stuff which provokes thinking and makes us uncomfortable. Reminds me of a quote I read somewhere:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because sometimes you don’t see how ridiculous something is unless it is shown to you in a ridiculous light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t think much of the quote when I first came across it, but after listening to many serious comics (George Carlin, Bill Hicks, Bill Maher to name a few) I realize how true it is. It’s almost as if it makes sense. Here are &lt;a href=&quot;http://jamesaquilone.com/101-greatest-george-carlin-quotes/&quot;&gt;some gems&lt;/a&gt; from the man whom I consider to be a seer, and someone who saw the future 40 years ahead of time, George Carlin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m completely in favor of the separation of Church and State. My idea is that these two institutions screw us up enough on their own, so both of them together is certain death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Religion has convinced people that there’s an invisible man…living in the sky, who watches everything you do every minute of every day. And the invisible man has a list of ten specific things he doesn’t want you to do. And if you do any of these things, he will send you to a special place, of burning and fire and smoke and torture and anguish for you to live forever, and suffer and burn and scream until the end of time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;But he loves you&lt;/em&gt;. He loves you and he needs money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/ChpKhpk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humor is all the more important in the ever-busy lifestyles that have become the reality of the day. Nobody today has got time to kick their heels and chill in the middle of the week, unless you’ve already ‘made it’. With our lives running like clockwork and rising stress levels, humor is the much-needed medicine that the old proverb talks about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is short. And nobody ever got out alive. Seriousness is not the best trait if you want to live a happy life. As I recall reading:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sincere; not serious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Science, bitches!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/22/science-bitches/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 05:19:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/22/science-bitches/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Science is about more than asking questions. &lt;a href=&quot;http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/21/the-importance-of-asking-questions.html&quot;&gt;Asking questions&lt;/a&gt; most certainly is step 0. The next step is about finding out the unknown, or to build the inexistent. As I like to think, science has 2 feet: discovery and invention. While discoveries keep the clock ticking and help us solve tough problems, inventions make life easier. Using it’s powers of reasoning and questioning, it has improved the quality of life tremendously over the years.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science is also about refusing to accept “God’s will” and covering unchartered territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For ex. People used to “naturally” die in their thirties; famines and diseases were supposed to be God’s wrath for something that made him unhappy. Rains, volcanoes, eclipses and natural phenomena were mysteries. Most of them have been figured out; and we have used that knowledge to advance the life span and the quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this would have been possible had we taken the general religious attitude, which happens to be: things are this way because God wants them to be this way. Taking things for how they are and not questioning are the biggest disservice you can do to your life and to your power of thinking, IMHO. If you take everything at their face value, you essentially end up living a life as dictated by others. In other words, you’re living their life. It makes you redundant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was brought up religious, and I always used to wonder: “Why does the omnipresent omnipotent God let kids die of diseases when he could have prevented them?” Essentially, I too had this doubt, and I’m certain I’m not alone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/Pxov2oe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s always good hidden in God’s plan” was another idea I was fed as a child. This broke down when I noticed all the wars, atrocities and pain in the world happening to innocents. I mean, seriously, a 5-year old child is raped and dies. Is this God’s plan? If so, I’m not sure I can have faith in that God anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently there was a big natural catastrophe that took a life of thousands of people who, ironically, were on a pilgrimage to God’s shrine. This probably was the last strand that even more strengthened my resolve in not buying this story anymore and finding out for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless we ask questions, we wouldn’t try to see beyond the craziness that the established norm is. And science is the way to do that. Science, and humor. Because sometimes you don’t see how ridiculous something is unless it is shown to you in a ridiculous light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out this beautiful comic by clicking on the image below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://zenpencils.com/comic/52-phil-plait-welcome-to-science/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-k337SBycQfs/Uj6Ah-sNgkI/AAAAAAAAE9k/YqEFQ6N0ij0/s640/2012-06-05-philplait.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Welcome to science&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Importance Of Asking Questions</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/21/the-importance-of-asking-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2013 07:30:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/21/the-importance-of-asking-questions/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We humans are the dominant species on this planet (or so we like to believe; I wouldn’t get into the microbial side of the story because this post is not about that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have spent thousands of years learning and civilizing ourselves, and that is the reason we, as a species, have gained whatever knowledge we have about the world around us. That is one of the reasons for our survival while many other species came and went. That, and adapting ourselves to changing surroundings; and changing our surroundings to suit us.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a child becomes old enough to start observing things, notice how curious they are. Everything around them is new; they want to touch it, feel it, taste it. That is how we get the early lessons: fire should not be touched, avoid sharp objects. Fear of heights is evolutionary, from what I remember reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newer non-association theory is that fear of heights is an evolved adaptation to a world where falls posed a significant danger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acrophobia#Causes&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes sense for a new person to use our collective learning and experience to not go and try out things like poisons, or wild animals for the sake of learning about their dangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we live in a very different world from even 100 years ago. The world around us is changing much faster than our evolutionary instincts. The dangers that used to be around us are no longer the same. You can hit a car and be fatally hurt, but the likelihood of a bear ripping you apart in the middle of a city is very low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fears, then translate into the situations that make us uncomfortable. Public speaking, apparently is a bigger fear than death to many people. Others in the same category can include thinking from a new perspective while rejecting the collective knowledge, voicing our opinion in the midst of majority that is opposed to our ideas; and &lt;em&gt;gasp&lt;/em&gt; asking questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way the world can progress is if the people continuously question and challenge the existing beliefs. Till &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosa_Parks&quot;&gt;Rosa Parks&lt;/a&gt; asked to be seated in the front, black people in America were not allowed to. Till &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ram_Mohan_Roy&quot;&gt;Ram Mohan Roy&lt;/a&gt; questioned the practice of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sati_(practice&quot;&gt;Sati&lt;/a&gt;), widows were burnt alive on their husband’s pyre. Till someone choose to question the ‘world is flat and you fall of the edge’ belief, we knew so little of what things were really like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite having strong historical and anecdotal proofs of the fact that asking questions pushes the human race forward, most of us take the safer path. We accept what we are told without questioning ourselves or others as to why we are doing that. If there is one thing I’ve learnt, it is this: “Why?” is the most important question in the world. And whenever in doubt, ask “Why?”. It can provide clarity like few other things can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The habit of asking questions should be encouraged in children. Being naturally curious, everyone is a scientist when they’re children; asking how something works and what would happen if something was done. That is the reason we learn so much in the first 10 years of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But once we grow up, we start taking things to be the way they are, and just go with the flow. This is where the stagnation sets in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/bg1J7uW.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never stop questioning. That is the only way we can learn and grow, as individuals, and as a society.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Post A Day</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/20/one-post-a-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2013 02:49:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/20/one-post-a-day/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been extremely lazy when it comes to being regular about writing, even though it happens to be my self-confessed hobby and dream to read, write and live amongst books for the rest of my life. That, and traveling.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an attempt to put an end to the procrastination and get cracking. A shot in the dark, if you will. I’ve never put myself to a challenge publicly, till now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been inspired (still wondering whether I’m ready to use that word) by many people, like the girl &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.danceinayear.com/story/&quot;&gt;who taught herself to dance in a year&lt;/a&gt;, or this person &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jenniferdewalt.com/&quot;&gt;who is making a website everyday&lt;/a&gt;; and this guy, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theawl.com/2013/09/i-was-a-hated-hipster-meme-and-then-it-got-worse&quot;&gt;who can write stories almost magically fast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content I write will mostly be my thoughts, maybe a short story, or my take on anything going on around me. At this point, even writing a single line everyday counts. I remember reading this rule, saying something to the tune of, “if you really want to do something, but it keeps getting sidetracked, start with 2 minutes everyday”. And that’s what I’m going to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how it turns out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The NSA has programs that collect data on US Supreme Court Justices and elected officials, and they secretly provide it to Israel</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/12/the-nsa-has-programs-that-collect-data-on-us-supreme-court-justices-and-elected-officials-and-they-secretly-provide-it-to-israel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 11:11:54 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/12/the-nsa-has-programs-that-collect-data-on-us-supreme-court-justices-and-elected-officials-and-they-secretly-provide-it-to-israel/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/11/nsa-americans-personal-data-israel-documents&quot;&gt;Latest Snowden revelation&lt;/a&gt; makes things look as if the NSA was being run by Israel all along.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Snowden, we now know the NSA:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Had James Clapper lie under oath to us - on camera - to Congress to hide the domestic spying programs &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nationalreview.com/article/350699/clappers-lie-charles-c-w-cooke&quot;&gt;Occured in March, revealed in June&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warrantlessly accesses records of every phone call that routes through the US thousands of times a day &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jun/06/nsa-phone-records-verizon-court-order&quot;&gt;June&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.politico.com/story/2013/09/nsa-broke-rules-call-tracking-96571.html&quot;&gt;September&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Steals your private data from every major web company (Facebook, Google, Apple, Microsoft, et al) via PRISM&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jun/06/us-tech-giants-nsa-data&quot;&gt;June&lt;/a&gt; and pays them millions for it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/aug/23/nsa-prism-costs-tech-companies-paid&quot;&gt;August&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pays major US telecommunications providers (AT&amp;amp;T, Verizon, et al) between $278,000,000-$394,000,000 annually to provide secret access to all US fiber and cellular networks (in violation of the 4th amendment). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/nsa-paying-us-companies-for-access-to-communications-networks/2013/08/29/5641a4b6-10c2-11e3-bdf6-e4fc677d94a1_story.html&quot;&gt;August&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Intentionally weakened the encryption standards we rely on, put backdoors into critical software, and break the crypto on our private communications &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/09/06/us/nsa-foils-much-internet-encryption.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;_r=1&amp;amp;&quot;&gt;September&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;NSA employees use these powers to spy on their &lt;strong&gt;US citizen&lt;/strong&gt; lovers via LOVEINT, and only get caught if they self-confess. Though this is a felony, none were ever been charged with a crime. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-switch/wp/2013/08/24/loveint-when-nsa-officers-use-their-spying-power-on-love-interests/&quot;&gt;August&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lied&lt;/strong&gt; to us again just ten days ago, claiming they never perform economic espionage (whoops!) before a new leak revealed that they do all the time. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/09/nsa-spying-brazil-oil-petrobras&quot;&gt;September&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Made over fifteen thousand false certifications to the secret FISA court, leading a judge to rule they “frequently and systemically violated” court orders in a manner “directly contrary to the sworn attestations of several executive branch officials,” that &lt;strong&gt;90%&lt;/strong&gt; of their searches were unlawful, and that they “repeatedly misled the court.” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/10/nsa-violated-court-rules-data-documents&quot;&gt;September&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.wsj.com/washwire/2013/09/10/five-revelations-from-new-nsa-documents/?mod=e2tw&quot;&gt;September&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has programs that collect data on US Supreme Court Justices and elected officials, and they secretly provide it to Israel regulated only by an honor system.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/11/nsa-americans-personal-data-israel-documents&quot;&gt;September&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/worldnews/comments/1m73n4/nsa_shares_raw_intelligence_including_americans/cc6hdm2&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feelings about AngularJS</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/11/feelings-about-angularjs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2013 16:14:20 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/09/11/feelings-about-angularjs/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://rockerhome.files.wordpress.com/2013/09/feelings_about_angularjs_over_time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Feelings about AngularJS&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funny depiction of what you go through while learning Angular.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atwood's Law</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/08/26/atwood-s-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26  Aug 2013 08:29:59 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/08/26/atwood-s-law/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2007/07/the-principle-of-least-power.html&quot;&gt;Any application that &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be written in JavaScript, &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; eventually be written in JavaScript. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting. On the note of laws related to software, check &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globalnerdy.com/2007/07/18/laws-of-software-development/&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://haacked.com/archive/2007/07/17/the-eponymous-laws-of-software-development.aspx&quot;&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The end of privacy as we know it</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/08/07/the-end-of-privacy-as-we-know-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07  Aug 2013 16:20:43 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/08/07/the-end-of-privacy-as-we-know-it/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember Eric Schmidt saying something to the effect of “if you don’t want something to be publicly known, don’t post it on the internet”. But as we have seen with the deeper proliferation of ‘social media’ on our lives, we can’t stop but share every moment of our lives online.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; There are specialized channels for us to share different types of content. I’m not here to rave about how the definition of words ‘share’, ‘like’ and ‘social’ has been &lt;del&gt;perverted&lt;/del&gt; changed over the last few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are enormous psychological and social effects of social media about which tons has already been written. This post has been motivated by what we have lately learned about all that has been going on in the past many years unbeknownst to mere mortals outside the high echelons of the government and corporates that we so willingly give all our information to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest revelation regarding what governments are keeping from their citizens was done by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden&quot;&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/a&gt; who sought refuge in Hong Kong and is currently in Russia. The US government has charged him with Espionage Act, among others. Previously, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bradley_manning&quot;&gt;Bradley Manning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Julian_Assange&quot;&gt;Julian Assange&lt;/a&gt;, the founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://wikileaks.org&quot;&gt;Wikileaks&lt;/a&gt; (also see: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1837703/&quot;&gt;The Fifth Estate&lt;/a&gt;) have been charged with accounts of passing private information to the enemy. While I am no one to judge the ramifications of what they have done, I do have one question. What about &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_R._Clapper&quot;&gt;James Clapper&lt;/a&gt;, the head of the NSA, who lied to the Congress about the existence of PRISM, the gargantuan data-collection program which the NSA is using to collect data from various software companies’ servers; which in turn, happens to be data of every individual, US citizen or not, who uses websites and services of these companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week a new incident followed the already snowballing set of activities in this space. The founder of Tor network was arrested after the government agencies &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cryptocloud.org/viewtopic.php?f=14&amp;amp;t=2951&amp;amp;sid=2113756b8111517e2678449f7056542e&quot;&gt;intercepted&lt;/a&gt; and added malware to the Tor network and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2013/08/freedom-hosting/&quot;&gt;Freedom Hosting&lt;/a&gt; using infected nodes. The Tor client, which was &lt;a href=&quot;http://pastebin.mozilla.org/2777139&quot;&gt;Mozilla Firefox ESR 17, had a vulnerability&lt;/a&gt; which was compromised in this attack. Here is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/mbijon/6151638&quot;&gt;source code of the malware&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently this malware was &lt;a href=&quot;http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2013/08/researchers-say-tor-targeted-malware-phoned-home-to-nsa/&quot;&gt;collecting data and sending to an IP&lt;/a&gt; which was one of the many IPs assigned to the government agencies. Exactly who was controlling it, is not yet clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Geolocation for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23torsploit&amp;amp;src=hash&quot;&gt;#torsploit&lt;/a&gt; server corresponds with Verizon&amp;#39;s secure government ops center &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/IxHJJgt247&quot;&gt;http://t.co/IxHJJgt247&lt;/a&gt; (thanks &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sidewalksuper&quot;&gt;@sidewalksuper&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kevin Poulsen (@kpoulsen) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kpoulsen/statuses/364462049130061824&quot;&gt;August 5, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script async src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security expert Bruce Schneier has this to say &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2013/08/nsa_surveillanc.html&quot;&gt;about the NSA surveillance&lt;/a&gt;. I used to have a lot of respect for America because of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q49NOyJ8fNA&quot;&gt;what it stood for&lt;/a&gt;. Those values seem to be decaying. The ‘land of the free; home of the brave’ is the one which is now headed to prosecute the people who told the public what their government is secretly doing with their personal data. This sounds a lot like ‘shoot the messenger’ to me. As Carlin used to say, the only American value that has remained, is buying things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/yt49DsfKDMc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the risk of sounding clichéd, I will leave you with one word: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nineteen_Eighty-Four&quot;&gt;1984&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What if Google starts doing it?</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/05/27/what-if-google-starts-doing-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 06:59:35 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/05/27/what-if-google-starts-doing-it/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This has been a question I have come across many times, and must say, is not a pointless one. I have been asked this by my friends many times I discuss an idea with them, and Google told me that &lt;a href=&quot;http://whatifgoogledoesit.com/&quot;&gt;many VCs do it&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always loved Google. For their culture, for the simple UI of their products, for supporting open technologies, for providing high-quality products (mostly) for free, unless you are a power user; and for tackling big problems. Theoretically, many of those things are still valid. But there is a problem. I am no longer a student, and when I pick a product, especially for professional use, I have to know that it will work, I will get the support in case I need it; and most importantly, it will still be around 6 months or 2 years from now. That is where this argument has started faltering lately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure Google is not abandoning GMail anytime soon. But can I be certain about things like Blogger, Calendar, or Feedburner? Not with certainty, I suppose. They’ll notify us in their Spring Cleaning updates and give time to export the data, but I still don’t see why shouldn’t I just stick to a company that is focused on that one product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to do something they are already doing, I think you should not let this fact be the sole deterrent, as long as you know there is a market and you know that you can provide a solid product and good support.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Real Story Behind Facebook Moderation and Your Petty Reports</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/04/16/the-real-story-behind-facebook-moderation-and-your-petty-reports/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2013 13:42:44 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/04/16/the-real-story-behind-facebook-moderation-and-your-petty-reports/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The other perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theinternetoffendsme.wordpress.com/2013/04/09/the-real-story-behind-facebook-moderation-and-your-petty-reports/&quot;&gt;Read the original story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some amazing answers I came across on StackOverflow</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2013/04/08/some-amazing-answers-i-came-across-on-stackoverflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 20:12:29 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2013/04/08/some-amazing-answers-i-came-across-on-stackoverflow/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Very descriptive and well-written. Not to mention long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/739654/understanding-python-decorators#1594484&quot;&gt;Decorators in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/100003/what-is-a-metaclass-in-python/6581949#6581949&quot;&gt;Metaclass in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/231767/the-python-yield-keyword-explained/231855#231855&quot;&gt;Yield in Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to The Matrix</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/11/26/welcome-to-the-matrix/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Nov 2012 14:18:05 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/11/26/welcome-to-the-matrix/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have entered the second generation of ‘machine generation’ with 3D printers. Till now we used to have machines assembling machines from parts. For example, a robot in a car factory building a car.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; [UPDATE: link added] &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/autopia/2013/02/3d-printed-car/&quot;&gt;Now we can ‘print’ cars&lt;/a&gt;, or their parts thereof using a 3D printer. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with every technology, as 3D printers get smaller, more efficient, faster and cheaper, I can almost visualize future machines having their own ‘healing units’ which can create and replace a part that has been worn out. Take it a step further and you can have fully self-spawning machines, not quite unlike living beings today. And with huge acceleration provided to machine learning thanks to big data and miniaturized supercomputing, those machines could take decisions, and think for themselves. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I give it 20 years to see ourselves living in a world filled with a completely different generation of machines, which are very close to humans in capabilities. I was reading the other day that in 20 years machines will know how to be funny, creative and, wait for it, sexy. The processing capabilities of your cell phone today, which is more powerful than yesteryears’ supercomputer, could be packed into something the size of a blood cell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On one hand we have the possibility of killing cancer cells by injecting intravenous supercomputers into the blood and keep a constant tab on our health. On the other, I wonder if it would be possible to monitor (and control?) people’s behavior using similar micro-gadgets. An extended version of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0368008/&quot;&gt;The Manchurian Candidate&lt;/a&gt; could perhaps become reality?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if someday machines will be ‘employing’ humans and patenting (imprisoning?) the intelligent ones. The possibilities, as they say, are endless. Would you like to be harvested for energy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS&lt;/strong&gt;: Did you ‘hear’? A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/design/2012/12/3-d-printed-record/&quot;&gt;3D printed record&lt;/a&gt; has been created in the lab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE&lt;/strong&gt;: It has been 3 months since I wrote this post and we already have a 3D printed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/autopia/2013/02/3d-printed-car/&quot;&gt;car&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medgadget.com/2013/02/cornell-bioengineers-3d-print-living-replacement-ears.html&quot;&gt;ear&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, the organ. I’m not saying I saw it coming, but I remember people saying that I was fantasizing and it was too far in the future to think about. Maybe not that far, after all. I’m excited!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Walking the slow road</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/11/16/walking-the-slow-road/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2012 12:43:03 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/11/16/walking-the-slow-road/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I took my ‘annual’ break at Deewali this year, and decided to stay completely out-of-touch from the internet. Here are my experiences.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Some of them might be super-obvious: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The information superhighway with all its hustle and bustle combined with the fast-paced lifestyles of our times can give rise to some problems unforeseen in the previous times. For instance, there have been reports of ‘withdrawal symptoms’ in Facebook addicts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking a detour from this overcrowded noisy road is not only useful, but most definitively necessary every once in a while.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;‘Normal’ people don’t spend their days and nights checking Twitter and Hacker News streams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One sad realization: Facebook has become the ‘high point’ in some people’s otherwise mundane lives, and hence, is acting as a drug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is humongous amounts of information being generated every second with the democratization of publishing media and the internet. As a result, the signal-to-noise ratio has gone down tremendously. And sites like Facebook with their revenue generation mechanisms &lt;a href=&quot;http://ninjasandrobots.com/facebook-pages-nest-thermostat&quot;&gt;aren’t helping&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is almost impossible to believe that it was no longer than 7-8 years ago when we didn’t have to ‘stay forever connected’ and yet had fulfilling lives and relationships. I have reasons to believe that was good for a lot of reasons, for example, debates on some topics could last for hours without having a clear sense of ‘right directions’. Now most of the topics that you can do such debates on are the eternal ones, like philosophy or religion.
Overall, it was fun taking a break. I intend to take more of these shut-offs going forward (lasting weekends, for instance).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Eulogy</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/11/09/a-eulogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2012 06:00:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/11/09/a-eulogy/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Note: I am publishing this post backdated to when I wrote it, because I was in &lt;a href=&quot;http://bhashkar.me/2012/11/16/walking-the-slow-road/&quot;&gt;internet detox&lt;/a&gt; back then]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night my father received a call. The caller informed that Mukesh was no more. Mukesh, as I recalled from 2 years ago, was probably one of the youngest people I had met working at that branch of the bank my dad works with. He was 33.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had only had one meeting with Mukesh, back in 2010. Other than that, there were a couple of times I ran into him at the bank. And we talked a few times on the phone. There isn’t much you can gather from such short encounters with a person, but there were some things that caught my eye. For one, it was hard not to notice him, because of his XXXL frame which, I think, was due to some metabolic anomaly. He was a jovial fellow, as some say most chubby people are. But he was also well read, quite literally, because as he told me, books were all he spent his money on, and that he had a home full of books. I intended to check out the collection someday, but that never happened; because on my vacations last year I got to know that he had moved to another city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll just share my recollections of one brief meeting we had at that coffee house of which even the name I can’t recall right now. We talked about life, dreams and careers. He told me how he got into banking, which was a very interesting story. He had a crush on this girl in his neighborhood, and she was prepping for the banking entrance exams. While she asked our man to help her with mathematics, if I remember correctly, he thought of taking the test himself, well, for kinda obvious reasons. What ended up happening, though, was that he cleared the exam while the girl didn’t. I’m guessing it was our very familiar “let’s grab the opportunity at hand” thought that caused him to enroll for the training. He confided in me that he didn’t really find the work exciting or challenging and was thinking of heading for his PhD and moving into the education sector which I wished him luck for. I talked about how I was enjoying and loving my work and having fun while learning a lot. We parted after that, since it was a chilly winter evening. After that the couple of conversations I had with him were mostly around some banking procedure I wanted to know about, or general pleasantries. And all of a sudden, now this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incident reminded me of this part from Steve Jobs’ famous &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF8uR6Z6KLc&quot;&gt;speech&lt;/a&gt;: “your time is limited, so don’t waste it living someone else’s life. Don’t be trapped by dogma, which is living with the results of other people’s thinking. Don’t let the noise of others’ opinions drown out your inner voice. And most important, have the courage to follow your heart and intuition. They somehow already know what you truly want to become. Everything else is secondary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As was also mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1187043/&quot;&gt;3 idiots&lt;/a&gt;: “if you don’t gather the courage now, you will wish you had done things differently when you are 60 and lying on a hospital bed, but it would be too late by then.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing how conveniently we all choose to ignore the one simple and definitive truth of life: we all are going to die. Either it will be without warning, or we would have lost so much time that we would be left with nothing else but regret. Maybe this ignorance comes from the discomfort that would happen from staring death in the eyes, maybe we think that thinking about death will take our happiness away for good. Maybe it’s helpful living in denial of the single biggest truth of life. Maybe it’s something else. But one thing doesn’t change. Death is coming. To all of us. The time is slipping rapidly. There’s only two options: watch it all happen, or do something worthy with what you have. I wonder if Mukesh had done things differently instead of continuing to work at a job he didn’t enjoy if he had known this a year ago. I wonder…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[I have intentionally left out some details out of respect for Mukesh and his family]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My talk at Droidcon Hacknight</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/10/30/my-talk-at-droidcon-hacknight/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2012 11:17:44 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/10/30/my-talk-at-droidcon-hacknight/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/oYiSuxPpJTg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a talk about hybrid vs native apps I gave at the Droidcon &lt;a href=&quot;http://hacknight.in&quot;&gt;Hacknight&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://hasgeek.com&quot;&gt;Hasgeek&lt;/a&gt;. Oh, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobstac.com&quot;&gt;we&lt;/a&gt; are look for Android Hackers. Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jobs.hasgeek.com/view/9epjg&quot;&gt;job posting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT:&lt;/strong&gt; Great news! &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.firstpost.com/topic/place/bangalore-droidcon-2012-hacknight-talks-building-hybrid-apps-at-mobs-video-oYiSuxPpJTg-3826-3.html&quot;&gt;Firstpost covered the story&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The plight of shortlinks</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/10/08/the-plight-of-shortlinks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2012 10:40:14 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/10/08/the-plight-of-shortlinks/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning, it turns out, t.co, twitter’s own URL shortner links were not working. The browser responded with ‘Lookup failed’, while wget said this:&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-bash&quot;&gt;Resolving t.co (t.co)... failed: nodename nor servname provided, or not known. 
wget: unable to resolve host address `t.co&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I tried to look into what was going on. This potentially meant that almost all of the millions of links being shared on twitter were rendered useless. Here’s what whois revealed: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-bash&quot;&gt;Domain Name: T.CO
Domain ID: D740225-CO
Sponsoring Registrar: MELBOURNE IT LTD
Sponsoring Registrar IANA ID: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;
Registrar URL (registration services): www.melbourneit.com.au
Domain Status: clientDeleteProhibited
Domain Status: clientHold
Domain Status: clientTransferProhibited
Domain Status: clientUpdateProhibited
Domain Status: serverDeleteProhibited
Domain Status: serverTransferProhibited
Registrant ID: TWITTERREG2012
Registrant Name: Twitter, Inc.
Registrant Organization: Twitter, Inc.
Registrant Address1: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1355&lt;/span&gt; Market Street
Registrant Address2: Suite &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;900&lt;/span&gt;
Registrant City: San Francisco
Registrant State/Province: CA
Registrant Postal Code: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;94103&lt;/span&gt;
Registrant Country: United States
Registrant Country Code: US
Registrant Phone Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.4152229670&lt;/span&gt;
Registrant Facsimile Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.4152220922&lt;/span&gt;
Registrant Email: domains@twitter.com
Administrative Contact ID: TWITTERADMIN2012
Administrative Contact Name: Domain Admin
Administrative Contact Organization: Twitter, Inc.
Administrative Contact Address1: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1355&lt;/span&gt; Market Street
Administrative Contact Address2: Suite &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;900&lt;/span&gt;
Administrative Contact City: San Francisco
Administrative Contact State/Province: CA
Administrative Contact Postal Code: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;94103&lt;/span&gt;
Administrative Contact Country: United States
Administrative Contact Country Code: US
Administrative Contact Phone Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.4152229670&lt;/span&gt;
Administrative Contact Facsimile Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.4152220922&lt;/span&gt;
Administrative Contact Email: domains@twitter.com
Billing Contact ID: MIT_BILLING
Billing Contact Name: DBS Billing
Billing Contact Address1: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;636&lt;/span&gt; Ellis Street
Billing Contact City: Mountain View
Billing Contact State/Province: CA
Billing Contact Postal Code: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;94043&lt;/span&gt;
Billing Contact Country: United States
Billing Contact Country Code: US
Billing Contact Phone Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.8669073267&lt;/span&gt;
Billing Contact Facsimile Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.6506182574&lt;/span&gt;
Billing Contact Email: billing@melbourneitdbs.com
Technical Contact ID: TWITTERTECH2012
Technical Contact Name: Tech Admin
Technical Contact Organization: Twitter, Inc.
Technical Contact Address1: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1355&lt;/span&gt; Market Street
Technical Contact Address2: Suite &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;900&lt;/span&gt;
Technical Contact City: San Francisco
Technical Contact State/Province: CA
Technical Contact Postal Code: &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;94103&lt;/span&gt;
Technical Contact Country: United States
Technical Contact Country Code: US
Technical Contact Phone Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.4152229670&lt;/span&gt;
Technical Contact Facsimile Number: +&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1.4152220922&lt;/span&gt;
Technical Contact Email: domains-tech@twitter.com
Name Server: NS1.P34.DYNECT.NET
Name Server: NS2.P34.DYNECT.NET
Name Server: NS3.P34.DYNECT.NET
Name Server: NS4.P34.DYNECT.NET
Created by Registrar: INJECTCSR
Last Updated by Registrar: MELBOURNE IT LTD
Last Transferred Date: Mon Mar &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;58&lt;/span&gt; GMT &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2011&lt;/span&gt;
Domain Registration Date: Mon Apr &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;26&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;40&lt;/span&gt; GMT &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2010&lt;/span&gt;
Domain Expiration Date: Thu Apr &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;25&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;59&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;59&lt;/span&gt; GMT &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2013&lt;/span&gt;
Domain Last Updated Date: Mon Oct &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;38&lt;/span&gt; GMT &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2012&lt;/span&gt;

&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Whois database was last updated on: Mon Oct &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;35&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;46&lt;/span&gt; GMT &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2012&lt;/span&gt; &amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the last line? I’m guessing somebody messed around with DNS settings. Hopefully the nameservers around the world will pick it up sooner, than later. But the question is: is there a need for more ‘embedded’ URL shorteners, maybe baked into the browsers, kinda along the lines of &lt;a href=&quot;https://login.persona.org/&quot;&gt;Mozilla Persona&lt;/a&gt; for authentication?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Just noticed that TNW has already reported this and is &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4625646&quot;&gt;trending on HN&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This keeps getting hotter</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/27/this-keeps-getting-hotter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 21:22:22 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/27/this-keeps-getting-hotter/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m not pointing fingers, but iOS 6 is stripping off Google search referrer data.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; No, doesn’t seem to be an OS bug; Bing data is preserved (&lt;a href=&quot;http://searchengineland.com/ios-6-removes-all-google-search-referer-data-134560&quot;&gt;read more here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might be wrong, but you can’t ignore the big picture. Take this, and add to it the fact that Apple bid goodbye to Google Maps in its latest iOS update and you can start getting a clearer indication of things to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://massivegreatness.com/squeeze-my-hand&quot;&gt;Siegler puts it well&lt;/a&gt;. While you are at it, &lt;a href=&quot;http://massivegreatness.com/mobile&quot;&gt;take notice&lt;/a&gt;. Listen to what &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/here-is-the-plan-marissa-mayer-just-announced-to-yahoo-employees-2012-9&quot;&gt;Marissa Mayer is telling Yahoo!&lt;/a&gt; now. Or as we put it at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobstac.com&quot;&gt;MobStac&lt;/a&gt;,  Mobile is the new web. Also, &lt;a href=&quot;http://theamazingios6maps.tumblr.com/&quot;&gt;check out what iOS6 maps shows you&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here’s the customary dose of fun:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/QxVlBlhVuY8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caput Draconis</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/23/caput-draconis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 21:20:33 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/23/caput-draconis/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[The title is the first password mentioned in Harry Potter books]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always been paranoid about security, but in the last few weeks the paranoia has increased, especially since I read how &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2012/08/apple-amazon-mat-honan-hacking/all/&quot;&gt;hackers almost entirely erased the digital life of Mat Honan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; [Here’s the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2012/08/mat-honan-data-recovery/all/&quot;&gt;follow-up articles on how he got (a part of) his data back&lt;/a&gt; and then about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2012/09/cosmo-the-god-who-fell-to-earth/all/&quot;&gt;catching the hacker&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has done a great job by providing two-step verification. &lt;a href=&quot;http://support.google.com/accounts/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;amp;answer=180744&quot;&gt;Here’s how you can use it&lt;/a&gt;. I wish more services would provide such security-enhancing solutions. So today I set sail searching for the best ways to create passwords which are hard to guess and yet easily memorable by humans. I didn’t want to use a software/service for it because it tends to limit the number of places you can use the service to enter the password (apps on phones/tablets, for instance). I understand that they are a much safer way to go, but the dependency was something I wanted to stay clear of. For those interested in such software solutions, please check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.roboform.com&quot;&gt;roboform&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lastpass.com&quot;&gt;lastpass&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://directory.fsf.org/wiki/Gringotts&quot;&gt;gringotts&lt;/a&gt; :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to explain what has already been explained, and in ways much better than I possibly can, I’ll share the links with you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/codinghorror&quot;&gt;Jeff Atwood’s&lt;/a&gt; famous post about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2005/07/passwords-vs-pass-phrases.html&quot;&gt;Passwords vs Pass Phrases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microsoft’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microsoft.com/security/online-privacy/passwords-create.aspx&quot;&gt;guidelines&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/security/pc-security/password-checker.aspx&quot;&gt;password security checker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.soundpuzzle.com/passwords.html&quot;&gt;Soundpuzzle&lt;/a&gt; has one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And then there’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://world.std.com/~reinhold/diceware.html&quot;&gt;diceware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those interested in numbers, here’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datagenetics.com/blog/september32012/index.html&quot;&gt;the analysis of how ATM PIN numbers are spread&lt;/a&gt; across the possible 10,000 values (0000 - 9999) Hopefully yours is not one of the top 20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here’s an awesome &lt;a href=&quot;http://xkcd.com/936/&quot;&gt;XKCD post about password security&lt;/a&gt; :) Be safe. Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VirtualBox Guest Additions on Ubuntu Server 12.04</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/15/virtualbox-guest-additions-on-ubuntu-server-12-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2012 23:38:19 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/15/virtualbox-guest-additions-on-ubuntu-server-12-04/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While trying to set up the development environment for my site, I was having problems making VirtualBox Guest Additions let me share files with the host OS. The production env is Ubuntu Server 12.04 running on AWS EC2 so it was obvious I had to use a VM on the MacBook to ensure my dev env is in sync with the production.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a couple of tries failed, I decided to start fresh. I deleted the existing VM, churned out a new machine and installed Ubuntu Server 12.04 (Precise Pangolin) on it. Then I proceeded with installing the VirtualBox Guest Additions. For this, I mounted the VBoxGuestAdditions_4.1.6.iso on the machine and ran the following command on it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-bash&quot;&gt;sudo ./VBoxLinuxAdditions.run
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and here’s the output&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-bash&quot;&gt;Verifying archive integrity... All good.
Uncompressing VirtualBox &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;4.1&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt; Guest Additions &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; Linux.........
VirtualBox Guest Additions installer
Removing existing VirtualBox DKMS kernel modules ...done.
Removing existing VirtualBox non-DKMS kernel modules ...done.
Building the VirtualBox Guest Additions kernel modules
The headers &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; the current running kernel were not found. If the following
module compilation fails &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt; this could be the reason.

Building the main Guest Additions module ...done.
Building the shared folder support module ...fail!
(Look at /var/&lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;/vboxadd-install.log to find out what went wrong)
Doing non-kernel setup of the Guest Additions ...done.
Installing the Window System drivers ...fail!
(Could not find the X.Org or XFree86 Window System.)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned log file printed thus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-bash&quot;&gt;/tmp/vbox.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;/utils.c:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;122&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;: error: assignment of &lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;-only member ‘i_nlink’
/tmp/vbox.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;/utils.c:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;132&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;9&lt;/span&gt;: error: assignment of &lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;-only member ‘i_nlink’
/tmp/vbox.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;/utils.c: In &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; ‘sf_nlscpy’:
/tmp/vbox.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;/utils.c:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;563&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;: warning: passing argument &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; of ‘utf8_to_utf32’ from incompatible pointer &lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; [enabled by default]
include/linux/nls.h:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;53&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;: note: expected ‘unicode_t *’ but argument is of &lt;span class=&quot;built_in&quot;&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; ‘wchar_t *’
make[&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;]: *** [/tmp/vbox.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;/utils.o] Error &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
make[&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;]: *** [_module_/tmp/vbox.&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;] Error &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
make: *** [vboxsf] Error &lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
Creating user &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; the Guest Additions.
Creating udev rule &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; the Guest Additions kernel module.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This had me confused so I Googled for solutions. &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.ig.ma/notebook/2012/virtualbox-guest-additions-on-ubuntu-server&quot;&gt;Here’s one&lt;/a&gt; I stumbled upon and tried, but didn’t help fix the problem. Even though the problem was apparently occurring due to missing headers, adding them didn’t fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued searching and landed on &lt;a href=&quot;http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=1888470&quot;&gt;ubuntuforums&lt;/a&gt;. I followed &lt;a href=&quot;http://ubuntuforums.org/showpost.php?p=11517689&amp;amp;postcount=6&quot;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt; and voila! it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, looks like it is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.virtualbox.org/changeset/39224/vbox&quot;&gt;fixed changeset on Vbox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, peace was restored :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tip:&lt;/em&gt; You would need to edit /etc/group file and add your username, www-data and root thus in order for permissions on the shared directory to work: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;change &lt;strong&gt;vboxsf:x:1001:&lt;/strong&gt; line to &lt;strong&gt;vboxsf:x:1001:&lt;your-user-name&gt;,www-data,root&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quarter of a Century as an Earthling</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/04/quarter-of-a-century-as-an-earthling/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Sep 2012 17:35:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/09/04/quarter-of-a-century-as-an-earthling/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Having completed 25 years on this planet, I suddenly feel old :P and no longer a teenager (looks like it took me a while to get out of that one).&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wanted to share a couple of things I have learnt (forgive me if something doesn’t fit, I’m still learning).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here goes, in no particular order. &lt;em&gt;[Warning: Slur of clichés coming up]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/t6UCFOI.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;default&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Love yourself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Happiness is internal, and you are in full control of your own&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do what you &lt;a href=&quot;http://danshipper.com/love-is-right-in-front-of-you&quot;&gt;really enjoy doing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Books are the best things on the planet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attitude matters a lot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never miss a good chance to shut up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However solidly founded an institution might be, it generally begins to slack once its size exceeds a certain threshold&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chocolates are delicious&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some people are hard on the outside, but have a good heart. Others are sweet from the outside, but only because they want something. Some are just jerks. A few might be like Ferrero Rocher, though. Hold on to the gems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not everyone is meant to be a part of your life forever. Some people come as teachers, and leave once their job is done&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Always’ and ‘never’ are two words you should always remember never to use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have fun. Enjoy today. Be happy. I know all of them are clichés but they are that way for a reason&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most people do things not because they think it is the right thing to do, but because it makes them feel ‘at ease’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are only two things in life: gifts and lessons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The best route to real happiness is gratefulness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always be open to possibilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making mistakes is okay, as long as you continue to learn from them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quora.com/Being-Wealthy/What-are-some-things-that-money-cant-buy&quot;&gt;some things&lt;/a&gt; money can’t buy. Of those it can, mostly the effect &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quora.com/Wealthy-People-and-Families/What-does-it-feel-like-to-be-a-self-made-millionaire-under-the-age-of-25&quot;&gt;doesn’t last&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Its amazing how much we can learn; and fascinating how much we fail to&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never stop dreaming&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiences become memories and that’s all what remains in the end&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Destinations keep changing. It’s enjoying the journey that matters&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Atention to details is important ;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharing a very good &lt;a href=&quot;http://danshipper.com/159185755&quot;&gt;lesson&lt;/a&gt; I learnt this morning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep asking “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4VdO7LuoBzM&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/a&gt;“&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I'm offended!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/08/25/i-m-offended/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25  Aug 2012 04:37:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/08/25/i-m-offended/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Taking offense is our national sport and pastime. Like weddings. And cricket. [As a side note, thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/India_at_the_2012_Summer_Olympics&quot;&gt;Sushil, Yogeshwar, Saina and Mary Kom&lt;/a&gt; for reminding us that there are other sports in the World]. Someone should suggest adding the event of ‘taking offense’ to the Olympic games. It could entail 7 people sitting around a table trying to prove everyone else an ostrich with their head stuck in cemented ground. I’m sure we have a prize reserved in that. Unless &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.care2.com/causes/somali-comedian-shot-dead-after-making-islamist-jokes.html&quot;&gt;someone&lt;/a&gt; beats us to it.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can find reasons to get offended in space in the midst of the vacuum, or at the bottom of the sea. At any given point in time, you can pick up any newspaper and find someone seeking apology from someone because they said or did something which offended them, or their fishes. Maybe their cantaloupe. There is no dearth of people waiting to pound on you just because in some super freaking vaguely awesome way, you hurt their personal, religious or political beliefs, regardless of however outdated or senseless they might have been. Or because you stopped them from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21428714.000-miracle-buster-why-i-traced-holy-water-to-leaky-drain.html&quot;&gt;drinking drainage water&lt;/a&gt; thinking it was coming straight from God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is because of this zeal of excelling at our national sport that we are constantly looking for things to get agitated about. The whole situation makes me feel as if we’re in a classroom full of juvenile kids pulling each others’ legs, or ears. Just that, we are ready to go ahead and kill people and burn buses for the same reasons now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/N4vfTn2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With every passing day, my belief is reinforced that sense of humor and common sense are both super powers. Bigotry is not only counter productive, it is also a bit old-school, maybe off by a few centuries. I feel that we are creating more boundaries, instead of removing them as should be the result of globalization. My this belief might have been triggered due to information travelling faster than ever before, and us getting to know a lot more about what is happening in the world (including the places that didn’t exist in our information map) than we did in the past. Although some people just don’t want to come out of the 6th Century, or so it seems. I wouldn’t say anything more, for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hindustantimes.com/India-news/WestBengal/Professor-arrested-for-poking-fun-at-Mamata/Article1-839847.aspx&quot;&gt;fear of offending&lt;/a&gt; them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As lawmakers and policymakers, the governments could do things to improve situations; although I don’t see that happening. And how could it, when the people who are sitting &lt;a href=&quot;http://thinkers-pad.blogspot.in/2012/08/asaduddin-owaisi-khilafat-20.html&quot;&gt;in the Parliament&lt;/a&gt; don’t ‘get it’. All they seem to be interested in, are their vote banks. Anyway, lets not go there. Its a whole other thing. But it would have been really helpful if there were some sensible people handling the issue instead of what &lt;a href=&quot;http://in.reuters.com/article/2012/08/24/india-twitter-facebook-ban-social-media-idINDEE87N09V20120824&quot;&gt;seem to be novices&lt;/a&gt; with barely any competence with technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thought: If we really need to invent more issues to bother ourselves with, it is probably a sign of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mindhacks.com/2012/05/18/bbc-future-column-why-your-brain-loves-to-tune-out/&quot;&gt;persistence blindness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[image courtesy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10151863469072718&amp;amp;set=a.106074207717.119507.655212717&amp;amp;type=1&amp;amp;theater&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fuck Yeah!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/07/29/fuck-yeah/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2012 09:15:24 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/07/29/fuck-yeah/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Forbes is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/briancaulfield/2012/07/27/aol-unit-techcrunch-q2-adjusted-f-bomb-production-down-45/&quot;&gt;counting&lt;/a&gt; the number of fucks TechCrunch gives; and TC &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2012/07/27/fornicating-under-consent-of-the-king/&quot;&gt;hits back&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the whole episode amusing; specially the fact that they related it to &lt;a href=&quot;http://uncrunched.com&quot;&gt;Arrington&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://parislemon.com/&quot;&gt;Siegler&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsfwcorp.com&quot;&gt;Carr&lt;/a&gt; leaving TC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here’s a little something for you. After all, this is what the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internets&quot;&gt;internets&lt;/a&gt; are all about, no?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/q1dpQKntj_w&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CSS Margin In Percentage</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/07/12/css-margin-in-percentage/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2012 19:29:30 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/07/12/css-margin-in-percentage/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, this is funny; but only if it doesn’t come in the way of you getting things done on time. I was trying to assign percentage margin to a &amp;lt;div&amp;gt; and it kept throwing me off on the calculations. A bit of googling led me to this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mattsnider.com/css-using-percent-for-margin-and-padding/&quot;&gt;explanation&lt;/a&gt;. If you are giving padding/margin in percentage, due to some out-of-the-world reason it would calculate on the basis of the &lt;em&gt;width&lt;/em&gt; of the parent element; whether you are calculating left-right values for margin/padding, or the top-bottom ones. It beats me as to why is it this way. Let me know if you know the answer. Back to work!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Just For Fun</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/07/01/just-for-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 15:30:51 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/07/01/just-for-fun/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just the other day… &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; re, os
avi_re = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'(Friends)(\\.)(S)(01)(E)(?P&amp;amp;lt;epi&amp;amp;gt;.*?)(\\.)(DVDRip)(\\.)(XviD)(\\.)(avi)'&lt;/span&gt;
sub_re = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'(Friends)( )(-)( )(1)(\\.)(?P&amp;amp;lt;epi&amp;amp;gt;\w+)(?P&amp;amp;lt;name&amp;amp;gt;.*?)(\\(EN\\))(\\.)(sub)'&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; avi_f &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; filelist:
  &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; re.match(avi_re, avi_f):
    e = re.match(avi_re, avi_f).group(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'epi'&lt;/span&gt;)
    &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; sub_f &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; filelist:
      &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; re.match(sub_re, sub_f):
        ep = re.match(sub_re, sub_f).group(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'epi'&lt;/span&gt;)
        &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; e == ep:
          new = &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'Friends - 1.'&lt;/span&gt; + ep + re.match(sub_re, sub_f).group(&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'name'&lt;/span&gt;)
          os.rename(avi_f, new + &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'.avi'&lt;/span&gt;)
          os.rename(sub_f, new + &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'.sub'&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;because I can! ;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Setting up my own server, finally!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/06/24/setting-up-my-own-server-finally/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2012 13:55:45 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/06/24/setting-up-my-own-server-finally/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had bought the domain &lt;a href=&quot;http://bhashkar.me&quot;&gt;bhashkar.me&lt;/a&gt; a year back, but didn’t really use it for something worthwhile. It hit me when time came to renew the lease on that thing that it was something I could have made good use of, and I decided to.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next thing I know, I had got myself an &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com/free/&quot;&gt;AWS Free tier&lt;/a&gt; and decided to set up a micro-site of sorts. I started looking for best options for a basic platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get enraged, I know how awesome Wordpress is. It’s just that I wanted something more powerful and tinker-able. I came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://octopress.org&quot;&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt; in the process, but wasn’t really inclined towards it, because it is a Ruby setup, and I wanted to do my playing around in Python. No, it doesn’t have that much to do with being language-bound, but given the constraints of resources at hand, I didn’t really have the freedom to install three setups at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can all it luck (I prefer &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Law_of_attraction&quot;&gt;LoA&lt;/a&gt;) that the same day &lt;a href=&quot;http://rigoneri.com/&quot;&gt;Rodrigo Neri&lt;/a&gt; came up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://rigoneri.github.com/syte/&quot;&gt;Syte&lt;/a&gt;, a setup on top of &lt;a href=&quot;http://djangoproject.com&quot;&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; (it’s what you call getting what you wished for :) ) and there was no turning back for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(In case you’re wondering, his own website is built on top of Syte too) In the process of trying to get things working, I got a chance to play with &lt;a href=&quot;http://gunicorn.org&quot;&gt;Gunicorn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nginx.org/&quot;&gt;Nginx&lt;/a&gt; (although I’m not exactly a stranger to it), python &lt;a href=&quot;http://pypi.python.org/pypi/virtualenv&quot;&gt;virtualenv&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.postgresql.org/&quot;&gt;postgresql&lt;/a&gt; and a host of other utilities. There, I just revealed my setup to you. Now that I have a playground of sorts, I will try to tinker with things and post stuff here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ciao for now!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advertising</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/06/03/advertising/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2012 11:01:12 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/06/03/advertising/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Advertising is one of primary sources of revenue for many companies, and of primary expenditure for many others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to validate the humongous expenditure on adverts and to optimize the RoI, a lot of researches are conducted to create the right messaging and feeling around the product and the brand to improve the targeting and enhance the effect advertisements have on the audience.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Advertising is what enables us to know about the new products and companies in town, gives us options to choose from and thus provides for a better market (going by the age-old ‘Competition breeds excellence’ adage).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously that is how they try to instill good messaging, but it really annoys me how advertisements imply that the only thing missing in your life keeping you from being truly happy is the one product they are selling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the real world, especially in the big cities, there almost is no breathing space without ads. In fact, if you look around right now, I can almost assure you that you will come across at least one piece of advertising in one of the multiple forms available. I loved the concept of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adbusters.org/magazine/73/Sao_Paulo_A_City_Without_Ads.html&quot;&gt;a place without ads&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the ‘personalization’ and ‘social’ advent of the Internet, the targeting seems to have started hitting the ‘creepy’ limit, if you ask me. I mean, just because people on my friend list like jewelry does not mean I do too (yes, I’m referring to Facebook showing me all kinds of adverts regarding jewelry and fashion shopping). IMHO, the Google model is as good as online advertising gets. I’m not saying that there can’t be further innovation in the space, but showing ads of things I am actually searching for seems much more sensible to me than showing them to me when I’m communicating with the people in my life. Not just that, Facebook knows (almost) the deepest of your secrets and can sell them to other companies in lieu of advertising revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really think that the Advertising industry needs a breakthrough/overhaul, but maybe that’s just me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Killer App</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/06/03/the-killer-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2012 10:12:05 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/06/03/the-killer-app/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every once in a while, I used to come across this phrase (although the frequency has now diminished and gave way to &lt;em&gt;enter-successful-product&lt;/em&gt;-killer in recent times). Since 2007 there have been at least 20 so-called iPhone killers, and every few days we get to see a new self-proclaimed Facebook/Instagram/Google killer.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://rockerhome.files.wordpress.com/2012/06/appstore-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;What is The New Big Thing?&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking specifically about the Internet, I personally think that there is one Killer app: The Browser. It has existed since the text-only web days and moved into the primarily-mobile age of today without so much as flinching. Undeniably, a ton of native apps keep coming everyday which might provide a better experience than the browser (thanks to HTML5, that gap is closing fast) but most of them are ‘easy come, easy go’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has been working hard on something. Is it a browser? Is it an OS? It’s Google’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Chrome_OS&quot;&gt;Chrome OS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that it needs to be said, but the browser is here to stay. And I can’t wait to play an upcoming version of Need For Speed on my browser. Far fetched? I’m choosing to stay optimistic ;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turning of the tables</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/05/28/turning-of-the-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2012 10:44:06 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/05/28/turning-of-the-tables/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I landed on this &lt;a href=&quot;http://john.jubjubs.net/2007/06/14/a-pictures-worth-100m-users/&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; and it sounded pretty amusing to me. Why? Because when it was written, Apple was planning its dominance on the Web, as it seems. But here’s the point: &lt;a href=&quot;http://google.com/chrome&quot;&gt;something inexistent&lt;/a&gt; 4 years ago has the largest market share in the World today. It would not have been possible if it wasn’t for open standards and continuous push towards creating something better and, of course, Google.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://rockerhome.files.wordpress.com/2012/05/screen-shot-2012-05-28-at-10-27-14-am.png&quot; alt=&quot;Web Browser Market Share: Chrome overtakes IE&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check out the graph yourself here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser-ww-monthly-200807-201205&quot;&gt;http://gs.statcounter.com/#browser-ww-monthly-200807-201205&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bet nobody saw it coming. In the meanwhile, I hear Facebook is working on it’s own &lt;a href=&quot;http://parislemon.com/post/23826782868/is-facebook-about-to-buy-opera-to-create-own-facebook&quot;&gt;browser&lt;/a&gt; of sorts, and maybe even OS. And, Microsoft recently launched it’s own version of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://so.cl&quot;&gt;social network&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heartbreaks</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/05/06/heartbreaks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 May 2012 12:45:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/05/06/heartbreaks/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Disclaimer: Those who came looking for a teenage girl’s drama can go jump off their roofs now]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart was made to be broken. - Oscar Wilde&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First things first. When I say ‘heartbreak’, I’m not necessarily referring to the romantic kind (although more often than not it happens to be the case).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heartbreaks are an integral part of life. Necessary evil, if you will, that makes you stronger, and wiser. I had never thought that heartbreaks are key factors in growing up and having realizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always believed that there’s only two things in life: gifts and lessons. Heartbreaks clearly fall in the second bucket (at least initially), somewhere down the line you might eventually be able to see the ‘gift’ aspect of them too, which is when it all starts making sense and you are grateful that it happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a problem. Trying to put it simply: I’m not one of those people who fake a smile to your face to make you feel happy while cursing you under their breath at the same time. I don’t believe in living a two-faced life. There’s many reasons behind that. One of the big ones being, I believe you’re spending way too much of your time and energy doing this. You’re lying to the other person, you’re lying to yourself and to anyone else who is a part of this mutual equation. And all this is pointless for people who are apparently not worthy of having a place in your life. Because if they were, you wouldn’t have taken the two-faced route to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-G-HJL7pEC-E/T6ZprbknUTI/AAAAAAAAA3o/CbGZA01ZctM/s1600/Two-Face_HarveyDent_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are downsides to my approach. I get over-attached to people at times. This is mostly when things hurt. Its pretty obvious: the only people that can hurt you are the ones whom you give a power to do so. A random guy walking on the road hurling abuses at you wouldn’t probably hurt you a hundredth of someone special ignoring you for a day. This is a realization to hold on to. Because I remember reading somewhere: “People will hurt you. Sometimes even if they don’t mean to.” Maybe just because your expectations of them are different from what they consider your relationship to be. The point here is about accepting this fact. One thing you can do (and I recommend doing this with a bit of sensibility rather than in a bout of emotion) is make the other person clear about what you think and feel about them. I have personally believed and experienced that having a clear and open communication is the most important piece, almost like a lifeline to any relationship, not just the romantic ones. That, and mutual respect for each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside to heartbreaks is, you get to know the REAL people. Both of their faces, in some cases. And that, I think is one big reason to be grateful for; since you know just what to do with them now. Heartbreaks teach you to become wiser and put more effort into understanding the other person. They help you understand what people can do and be. They make you able to tell similar people to fuck off the next time you come across one. Beware, heartbreaks can also make you into a wry person, which is something you should watch out for. Nobody in the World should be able to change who you are at the core. If they are able to, that just means you are doing what they essentially wanted you to. I would never lose to people who never deserve me in their life, let alone become more like them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emotion that can break your heart is sometimes the very one that heals it… - Nicholas Sparks, At First Sight&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote reminded me of a song:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/5vO9qp9cx4Q&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you’re going to get your heart broken. And it isn’t just going to happen once, but a lot. That’s just part of growing up, and it makes you stronger. Then you can handle it better next time. You may not get through it yourself, but your friends will help you through it. And you’ll be a stronger person because of it. Then one day someone will come along, and it’ll all pay off and no one will ever break your heart again. Always have good friends around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you one of those who think love and romance are overrated, and only meant to sell Valentine’s Day cards? I don’t care what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was, and remain, a hopeless romantic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hacking Django-Piston</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/05/06/hacking-django-piston/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 May 2012 11:29:59 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/05/06/hacking-django-piston/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobstac.com&quot;&gt;MobStac&lt;/a&gt;, we are working on building REST API support for the system. After evaluating various REST API framworks for &lt;a href=&quot;http://djangoproject.com/&quot;&gt;django&lt;/a&gt;, I chose to go with &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/jespern/django-piston/&quot;&gt;django-piston&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust me, there is hundreds of pages such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/656979/django-and-restful-apis&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; debating on which framework to go with, and amongst the top choices (alongside piston) were &lt;a href=&quot;http://django-rest-framework.org/&quot;&gt;Django REST Framework&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/django-rest-interface/wiki/RestifyDjango&quot;&gt;RESTify Django&lt;/a&gt; and others. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason we chose to go with piston is because of the use case we had; which is: an already existing web UI to perform actions, to which (at least for now) the API is going to be a supporting component. Piston is quite well-written, comes with out-of-the-box support for standard output formats (XML, JSON, YAML) and has Basic HTTP Authentication and OAuth built in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The down-sides, on the other hand, are that it is not well maintained, and there exist almost 150 forks to it, which people created to solve their own problem set. It would have been much better had there been an active support community and integrating features into piston.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I did not understand is the reason to why the author himself has forked it to create another repo that supports OAuth2. I mean, OAuth2 has essentially become the de-facto standard and OAuth has been phased out, especially by the majors (twitter and facebook).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally think it would have made more sense to deprecate OAuth support from the main branch. Anyways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;Update: &lt;/strong&gt;After reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://hueniverse.com/2012/07/oauth-2-0-and-the-road-to-hell/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; I want to take back what I said above about OAuth 2.0.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As has been my experience with using the plug-and-play frameworks, there are rarely the ones which, essentially, just work to suit your use case. I experienced the same thing when I was building the MobStac Authentication module and tried using &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/ubernostrum/django-registration/&quot;&gt;django-registration&lt;/a&gt;. It worked for a while, but soon we outgrew it’s capabilities (when we had to start adding support for Facebook/Twitter OAuth2 integration, or payment for example). Eventually we had to scrap it and write our own Auth module which, so far, has scaled well. Although there are traces of designs from django-registration remaining, which I intend to get rid of at some point of time. Piston was a similar case. It lacked support for customizing response keys if you wanted to use a Model handler. Let me explain. Django is built on the MVC architecture, except that its more MTV (Model-Template-View). A typical model looks such: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;class&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Book&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;(models.Model)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    title = models.CharField(max_length=&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;256&lt;/span&gt;, db_index=&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;)
    author = models.CharField(max_length=&lt;span class=&quot;number&quot;&gt;512&lt;/span&gt;, db_index=&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;)
    published = models.DateTimeField(db_index=&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Piston, with its default integration, allows you to create a handler which directly ties to a model:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;class&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;BookHandler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;(BaseHandler)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
     allowed_methods = (&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'GET'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'POST'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'PUT'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'DELETE'&lt;/span&gt;)
     fields = (&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'id'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'title'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'author'&lt;/span&gt; )
     model = Book
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good. My problem with this was that I can’t expose the ‘title’ field as ‘book_name’ or anything else if I wanted to. Piston did not have support for inbuilt mappings of such kind. The only way out would have been to write a method like so: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;class&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;BookHandler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;(BaseHandler)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
     allowed_methods = (&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'GET'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'POST'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'PUT'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'DELETE'&lt;/span&gt;)
     fields = (&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'id'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'book_name'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'author'&lt;/span&gt; )
     model = Book

&lt;span class=&quot;decorator&quot;&gt;@staticmethod&lt;/span&gt;
     &lt;span class=&quot;function&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;book_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;(object)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
         &lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; object.title
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which, I felt, was overkill to do each time I wanted a custom field name. So I chose to go ahead and modify the emitters module which processes the input format and returns the output. I have already &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/bhashkar/django-piston/&quot;&gt;forked&lt;/a&gt; piston, but yet have to apply the patch to it. Will do it soon, I promise. I also added Session-based authentication support to it. Now for the same outcome, all you need to do is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;class&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;BookHandler&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;params&quot;&gt;(BaseHandler)&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    allowed_methods = (&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'GET'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'POST'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'PUT'&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'DELETE'&lt;/span&gt;)
    fields = (&lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'id'&lt;/span&gt;, { &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'book_name'&lt;/span&gt; : &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'title'&lt;/span&gt; }, &lt;span class=&quot;string&quot;&gt;'author'&lt;/span&gt; )
    model = Book
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s right! I added yet another fork to the already present tons of piston forks in the World. C’est la vie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peace out, people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;strong&gt;PS:&lt;/strong&gt; You might be interested in reading this post by the author of Django about the REST API worst practices: &lt;a href=&quot;http://jacobian.org/writing/rest-worst-practices&quot;&gt;http://jacobian.org/writing/rest-worst-practices&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keep Looking. Don't Settle.</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/04/15/keep-looking-don-t-settle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2012 14:31:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/04/15/keep-looking-don-t-settle/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m going to spare you the usual dosage of ‘sorry I haven’t been active lately’ and get straight to the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading a bit too many college Commencement speeches lately&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (especially since I became a big fan of &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.stanford.edu/news/2005/june15/jobs-061505.html&quot;&gt;Steve’s&lt;/a&gt;; also check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://halfhalf.posterous.com/dont-work-be-hated-love-someone&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://movies.ndtv.com/movie_story.aspx?keyword=bollywood&amp;amp;ID=ENTEN20120199455&amp;amp;subcatg=MOVIESINDIA&amp;amp;nid=197063&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;) and there’s certainly commonalities amongst them. The most common messages that these successful and ‘great’ people have tried to pass on is: Dare to dream and be crazy enough to chase it. It certainly is the only way to happiness. Find something you love to do, and have fun doing it. Create new things. Give back to the world. Enjoy the journey. Family and friends are the most important parts of life. Fall in Love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes me think. Most people around us are not living their lives on these principles. Which also explains why they are ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H0qNil6--pE&quot;&gt;normal&lt;/a&gt;‘ and not SRK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was having this discussion with my colleagues the other day (being one of my favorite things to talk about, I probably have spent half of my last 1000 talking-hours discussing Life) where someone started with how lucky Army people are, living their suave lives and enjoying it. How they get to travel the country, and the World in some cases on official trips. How they get respected and have a different class of life compared to most civilians. When I brought up the ‘grass being greener on the other side’ argument, ‘there’s always lack of time in our current field of work’ was thrust into my face, to which, honestly I didn’t have a major counter-point. But I remember reading somewhere that the CEO of Yahoo! India (current or one of the past ones) spends weekends DJ-ing. This point was shot down with the logic that he’s the CEO and can do whatever the heck he wants to. I think it can’t be farther from the truth. For one thing, the higher you go in the chain of command, your responsibilities also increase (I guess linearly, if not exponentially). And also, if that guy is DJ-ing as the CEO, I’m sure he would have taken time out to continue devoting time to this hobby of his when he was NOT the CEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-jlqBnd29DsA/T4rAjIWSa7I/AAAAAAAAA1E/mW3ZXr9vaiE/s320/IMG_20120404_123247.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My first click on Instagram&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://instagram.com/&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/a&gt; is the hottest company in town as of now, because of the very recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2012/04/09/facebook-to-acquire-instagram-for-1-billion/&quot;&gt;Facebook acquisition&lt;/a&gt;. While reading the &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2012/04/09/instagram-story-facebook-acquisition/&quot;&gt;Instagram story&lt;/a&gt;, I remember reading that the founder of Instagram did not know how to code, he was a marketing guy. He learned to code while moonlighting along with his day work. (Oh, and his girlfriend learned to code too. It’s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2012/02/09/awwwwwwwwwwwwwwwwww/&quot;&gt;sweet story&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point I’m trying to make here is, its not easy in most cases. Most people have pursued what they wanted to do even when they didn’t have the time, energy or resources to. It reminds me of an great scene from a legendary movie by one of the most &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ywuse55qU2A&quot;&gt;inspiring people&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/fkIyE_bi3P0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(find the text for this scene &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0479143/quotes?qt=qt0349288&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J K Rowling wrote initial books of Harry Potter over 6 tough years filled with loss of family members, divorce and financial difficulties only to end up being rejected by 12 publishers till Bloomsbury said a ‘Yes’ and the rest, as they say, has touched the lives of millions of people (including your’s truly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s Rowling’s Harvard Commencement Address:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/wHGqp8lz36c&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure meant a stripping away of the inessential. I stopped pretending to myself that I was anything other than what I was, and began to direct all my energy to finishing the only work that mattered to me. &lt;em&gt;Had I really succeeded at anything else, I might never have found the determination to succeed in the one area where I truly belonged&lt;/em&gt;. I was set free, because my greatest fear had been realized, and I was still alive, and I still had a daughter whom I adored, and I had an old typewriter, and a big idea. And so rock bottom became a solid foundation on which I rebuilt my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I adore the part where she says she succeeded at what she loved because she failed at everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Steve said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve got to find what you love. And that is as true for your work as it is for your lovers. Your work is going to fill a large part of your life, and the only way to be truly satisfied is to do what you believe is great work. And the only way to do great work is to love what you do. If you haven’t found it yet, keep looking. Don’t settle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m the wrong guy to be giving an advice on success or what should you be doing with your life. But there is one thing I know. I enjoy what I do. I’m excited about my work. I know its neither Rocket Science nor is it saving people’s lives. But hey, it gets me excited! I’m in love with it. And I think that is what really matters. Having fun, while creating something beautiful and useful for people. That is what I’ve wanted to do. And I’m lovin’ it ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you love doing?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessons</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2012/01/04/lessons/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 12:25:19 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2012/01/04/lessons/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy 2012 folks! :) In Feb it will be two years since I started working. There are things that come obviously to people. Then there are the ones which take some time. There are the ones that everyone tells you do but you don’t follow until you’ve been bitten in the ass by not following them.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Here are a couple of things (my resolution for 2012? Lets call them that) that I’ve realized make life easier for you as a developer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use getter functions instead of directly referencing attributes. Helps you modify and control behavior in a much more centralized way (those from the Javaland, I know what you’re thinking :D ) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use debugging tools frequently: Breakpoints, logs, prints, inspectors. They’re there to save your sanity. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write self-contained and pluggable/reusable code, as much as is possible while maintaining the cleanliness and without making it over-pluggable. Then you’re just writing 2 lines of code to replace 1 line. Bad idea. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t write even ONE line of code until you have planned how to go about building whatever it is that you’re working on; be it a full project or a 3-line method. (Okay, there are exceptions to this one. But I’m gonna put it in anyways) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a pen-and-paper or a whiteboard to write down points rather than keep them in your head. Its much easier to revisit things this way. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk. Anything that you’re doing new or have even the slightest doubt on how to do/what is the best way to go about it; its best to pull in 1-2 people and explain what you are trying to accomplish. Maybe they will tell you an easier workaround. Even if they’re not able to answer, they might be able to ask questions that might help you come up with solutions that rule out the need to do, say, a big chunk of your task. [This one comes from the meeting after which we didn’t have to replicate our ALL databases, as we realized there was an easier solution out there]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Please note that these are just a few of those I have found helpful. This list is in no means comprehensive, complete or THE list. Also, these are things relevant to my development environment setup (python, django, mysql, mongodb, uwsgi, nginx etc.) Might be totally useless for you :) ] Oh look, its already the longest post on this blog till date. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adding from &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/nikunjlahoti&quot;&gt;@nikunjlahoti&lt;/a&gt;‘s comment:&lt;/em&gt; If you don’t want to code then just plz don’t please anyone by writing crap. or copy pasting snippets. just get a better job. &amp;amp; if u r stuck for good then look at the best-practices (at least). make lives easier.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are the odds! :D</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/12/01/what-are-the-odds-d/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2011 12:11:26 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/12/01/what-are-the-odds-d/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://rockerhome.files.wordpress.com/2011/12/screen-shot-2011-12-01-at-12-02-08-pm.png&quot; alt=&quot;I swear its real!&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While working on something I just thought of checking the system date (oh right, I was checking the NGINX logs) and very very coincidentally I landed on that. Thought it would be cool to upload it here ;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duplicate a MySQL database</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/19/duplicate-a-mysql-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 12:03:37 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/19/duplicate-a-mysql-database/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was testing something out, and realized that I needed to clone my database to run some tests while still being able to keep the data intact. And that’s when I started searching for a way to do it, and turns out there’s a one-liner to do the same :) &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;lang-sql&quot;&gt;# mysqladmin &lt;span class=&quot;operator&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;keyword&quot;&gt;create&lt;/span&gt; DB_name -u DB_user &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;--password=DB_pass &amp;amp;&amp;amp; \&lt;/span&gt;
mysqldump -u DB_user &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;--password=DB_pass DB_name |&lt;/span&gt;
mysql -u DB_user &lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;--password=DB_pass -h DB_host DB_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the site where I found it: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rubyrobot.org/article/duplicate-a-mysql-database&quot;&gt;http://www.rubyrobot.org/article/duplicate-a-mysql-database&lt;/a&gt; (although at this point of time I’m kinda feeling it was moot writing this post as anyone Googling for the solution can land on the page anyway :P )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gotta run! Peace out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>If you want to go for an MBA...</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/12/if-you-want-to-go-for-an-mba/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2011 03:47:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/12/if-you-want-to-go-for-an-mba/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Read this.. and keep in mind while reading that this talk has been given by a professor of IIMC and that the students were some of the best ones and would easily go ahead and bag the highest paying jobs out there (IIM grads, duh!)&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jokatimes.com/2010/11/08/i-have-a-dream-2/&quot;&gt;http://www.jokatimes.com/2010/11/08/i-have-a-dream-2/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Just in case it says ‘page unavailable’, scroll down. Seems to be some issue with the site)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read this &lt;strong&gt;AFTER&lt;/strong&gt; reading the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you’re done reading this, I implore you to take some time out and think. With all due respect to your knowledge and intelligence, its an obvious fact that the CAT is no piece of cake, and being able to score a seat in an IIM is one of the biggest proofs of a person’s capabilities. And the two years of studies after that are another feat to achieve. All in all, I’d say that you are more than two years of sleepless nights away from being where these people were when that talk was delivered (remember, they’re about to pass out) That being said, I don’t mean to demotivate or scare you. If this is what you TRULY want because you LOVE doing it, just go for it. The point I’m trying to focus on here is, after going through ALL of the hard parts which most of us intend to just for that astronomical paying job, they are NOT looking forward to that job (not most of them anyway) They want to go ahead and fulfill their dreams. Now, there can be one addition, which is, having an IIM degree with them, they would have much more credibility wherever they go. But is MBA the ONLY way ahead then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I’m trying to say is- doing something because it pays more, or because everyone* covets it are the worst possible reasons to make a career choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read somewhere that in a study they found that as long as you are in a stable and well-paying job (which I think all of us are and will be, given we continue to deliver) the ONLY thing that matters post-35 is the satisfaction. (I know, I know.. now you’d say you’ve got 10 years till you reach there. But how do you know this feeling wouldn’t start settling sooner? And to be happily doing something you love at 35, you’d need to put atleast a couple of years into it)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’ll quote my iCon Steve here (I do that often)- &lt;em&gt;“You’ve got to find what you love. And that is as true for your work as it is for your lovers. Your work is going to fill a large part of your life, and the only way to be truly satisfied is to do what you believe is great work. And the only way to do great work is to love what you do. If you haven’t found it yet, keep looking. Don’t settle. As with all matters of the heart, you’ll know when you find it. And, like any great relationship, it just gets better and better as the years roll on. So keep looking until you find it. Don’t settle.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/Hd_ptbiPoXM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* and here’s the funny realization that I had. When most of us want (here ‘want’ refers to truly wanting from the bottom of your heart) to follow our dreams, who is this ‘everyone’ that has such lame beliefs?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steve left us!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/05/steve-left-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2011 14:02:07 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/05/steve-left-us/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Its a sad sad day for the World :’-( I’ll try to write something once I gain composure. &lt;img src=&quot;http://rockerhome.files.wordpress.com/2011/10/steve-apple-home.png&quot; alt=&quot;The iCon&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My jsFoo talk</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/02/my-jsfoo-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2011 16:35:52 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/10/02/my-jsfoo-talk/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I got the opportunity to talk at &lt;a href=&quot;http://jsfoo.hasgeek.com&quot;&gt;jsFoo 2011&lt;/a&gt; organized by &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/hasgeek&quot;&gt;HasGeek&lt;/a&gt; which also happened to be my first talk since college.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Following is my presentation uploaded to SlideShare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe src=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/9505629&quot; width=&quot;427&quot; height=&quot;356&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px 1px 0; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&quot; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic of my talk was ‘Client-side rendering using &lt;a href=&quot;http://mustache.github.com/&quot;&gt;mustache.js&lt;/a&gt;‘ which is the nifty technique we have used in building &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobstac.com&quot;&gt;Touchsites&lt;/a&gt; at MobStac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/F5tG1pZ-g7g&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had fun at the event listening to other speakers and socializing with the people attending the event. I’m definitely looking forward to similar events. Feel free to contact me for more information :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Be careful with your /hosts file</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/09/15/be-careful-with-your-hosts-file/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 11:14:35 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/09/15/be-careful-with-your-hosts-file/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Never remove the mapping that points localhost to 127.0.0.1 in the /hosts file (location can vary depending on the OS).&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent 1 day trying to figure out why things were not working expectedly. The reason the issue occurred was because some daemon services running on the machine used the address localhost:port to communicate to each other (which makes perfect sense btw).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its just that I modified the localhost mapping from 127.0.0.1 to the network IP instead of adding a new entry for the same. You might be thinking: this guy only posts about problems, doesn’t he? Well, what can I say.. I’m still learning ;) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ciao for now!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Found a bug in the iPad!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/24/found-a-bug-in-the-ipad/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24  Aug 2011 17:34:47 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/24/found-a-bug-in-the-ipad/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Photos app hanged when I was moving photos around, zooming in and out. Has something to do with multi-touch. &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Googled it and found lots of people cribbing about the same on the Apple Forum :P Following is the screenshot after which I wasn’t able to do anything in the app. Had to close it and reboot the iPad. Did someone just scream ‘Windows’? :P !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://rockerhome.files.wordpress.com/2011/08/photo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Taken when the Photo app hanged on the iPad&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NEVER name a folder with a space character on a Unix machine</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/10/never-name-a-folder-with-a-space-character-on-a-unix-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10  Aug 2011 17:51:17 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/10/never-name-a-folder-with-a-space-character-on-a-unix-machine/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And when I say NEVER, I mean NEVER. Although you should ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_Z5-P9v3F8w&amp;amp;ob=av3e&quot;&gt;Never&lt;/a&gt; Say &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aihu16RyYp8&quot;&gt;Never&lt;/a&gt;‘ :P &lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this case I will. For the simple reason that a &lt;space&gt; character in the source of folder which Eclipse was running from made me waste a couple of my hours spread over 2 days to figure out what on the Earth was going on. It included reinstalling Pydev,  and at one point of time I actually considered reinstalling Eclipse. Then while checking out the error logs it suddenly hit me. I fixed it and Voila! There it was. Working the way it should have. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A suggestion to *NIX based OS developers: Please don’t give the default folder name such that it causes problems. Peace is restored to the World :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Only once</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/10/only-once/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10  Aug 2011 07:09:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/10/only-once/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I watched ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1562872/&quot;&gt;Zindagi Na Milegi Dobara&lt;/a&gt;‘; and loved it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe we all need reminders, to be brought back to our senses from the madness of the ever-running world to make ourselves realize that life is not a race.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Far from it, its a beautiful journey that we are taking and we have to remember to enjoy ourselves. If we don’t do that, all we would be left with would be fleeting memories and regrets of what could have been a wonderful journey, if only we had realized it in time. This reminds me of a beautiful story that I read. Will try to quote it below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s dawn and he is walking by the seashore. The sun has not yet risen, and the surroundings are semi-dark. Its been a bad season. Not many fish are left anywhere near the shore, and he can’t risk taking his old, frail boat to the deep waters. He doesn’t know whether it will manage to stand the waves for long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-yghiKCfz-eY/T6Z6FG88TzI/AAAAAAAAA30/GlwU94GvPbQ/s1600/orange_glow_of_the_dawn_sun_and_beauty_of_the_sky_reflecting_in_the_beach_and_sea.2560x1600.ba7662ff.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If only he had money. He would buy a big boat and catch more fishes. He would sell them to earn enough money till he doesn’t have to catch fish for a living anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly he noticed a small pouch lying near his feet. Intrigued, he picked it up. Maybe it contains some money that could help him live a better life. His dreams would then come true. In a combined state of excitement and nervousness, he opened the pouch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damn, it’s just a bag of pebbles. What a waste. He started cursing God for never giving him something of value while other people were living a rich and wonderful life. Its plain unfair. That’s what life is. In disappointment  he started throwing the pebbles one by one into the sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is destined to live a poor life. Once the sun comes up, like every other day he will take his boat into the sea to catch some fishes. That’s what he is going to have to do this for the rest of his life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably some kids were playing with this bag of pebbles. Maybe this was their make-believe money bag. Thinking of kids made him sad. He wants to raise a family. But he can’t. He’s barely able to feed himself with all the uncertainty in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many times he prays to the Almighty, although he has no idea whether such a thing exists. He has never seen Him ever. He has only heard from his parents that He listens and grants you the deepest desires of your heart if you ask with a true heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he thought about the people who had been trying to make him change his ‘religion’, whatever that meant. They told him their God was true and others were liars who were trying to take advantage of him by telling him to follow other Gods. This was something he never understood. For one thing he was the last person someone would gain something out of. He had no money and not many people knew him even in his neighborhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this happened to him a couple of times, he started telling them he did not believe that God existed, and that he had no interest in their ideas. This kept those God-salespeople away and he resumed to his life where his God was someone whom he talked to when he felt lonely. He shared his plans with him, asked him for money and a better life and everything; but nothing seemed to work. Slowly he himself started believing that God indeed was just a fragment of imagination and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bag of pebbles feels lighter. Looks like it’s been long, since I’ve thrown almost all of them into the water. Also dawn seems to be breaking. There are traces of light on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pebbles are almost finished. He emptied the pouch on his palm. Three pebbles remaining. He threw another one into water. The Sun is visible on the horizon. Its starting to get brighter with the red first light of the day. Maybe I should get ready to take my boat. This is early morning and not many people would be out in the sea. I might get enough fishes worth buying myself a couple of days of food. He threw another one. If only God had been more just to me. The Sun has risen to show his full round self. The surroundings have turned yellow like gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as he was about to throw the last pebble, he noticed something strange about it. It was glowing and transmitting the light coming from the Sun. Wait, is he seeing correctly? It. Can’t. Be. A diamond? He had heard about them that with a single one of these you could buy yourself a house, or a year worth of food. I can’t believe I threw hundreds of these into the sea. What a fool am I. When God gave me what I had been asking for, I didn’t realize what it was till I was left with but a speck of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried to keep the soul of the story intact while making changes. If you’re unable to get the analogy, get in touch :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And FYI, I’m ready for another visit to the multiplex to watch the movie again.
Let me know ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another weekend</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/07/another-weekend/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07  Aug 2011 10:38:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/08/07/another-weekend/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Haha.. gotcha! Misleading title indeed. :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So its Friendship Day. I am again overflowing with thoughts and emotions about a lot of things and people (happens to me from time to time, especially on such occasions).&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; I did not go ahead and text people ‘Happy Friendship Day’ for a reason- I wanted to wish each of them personally instead of just forwarding a message (no offense meant to anyone). Now as it happens, this might unravel over a period of time in the coming days. Don’t mark my words though. It all depends on how much time I am able to take out to compose each one of those messages, and also on how long this enthusiasm lasts :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, each of my friend means something different and special to me. The beauty of this World is that everyone is so unique that you never run out of things to be amazed about and learn from others, if you want to, that is. I thank God for every experience I have ever had in my life, regardless of whether at that point of time I considered them to be good or bad. In retrospect, everything eventually turns out for the best. We just need the faith and the patience to see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was watching F.R.I.E.N.D.S today and realized that I need to revisit the series. That’s a good thing, right? :) I also realized something else. I tend to have an emotional quotient of a character from a romantic movie. Don’t get me wrong. I am in total control of my emotions and everything. Its just that sometimes I feel that the intensity of emotions in me happens to be higher than that in ‘normal’ people. I tend to get close to people quicker than the ones who have their ‘guards’ up. I also get a vibe sometimes that that is interpreted by some people as me ‘hitting’ on them. Well, that’s their way of thinking. I can’t do much to change it. Although I don’t deny that I (for obvious reasons) am on the lookout for ‘the one’ as it happens to be. Just want to say that I happen to be the guy I pretend to be. I hate hypocrisy and two-faced people and I’d rather not be one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, I’m off to watch Zindagi Na Milegi Dobara. Peace out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meaning</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/07/17/meaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 13:33:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/07/17/meaning/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Alert: The tone of this post is going to be mostly philosophical. You may run now, if you wish]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is fun, humans are funny. I’m kinda lost on where to begin, but let me try.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to have a very curious thought-process. Many of you might even deem it crazy. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheldon_Cooper&quot;&gt;Sheldon Cooper&lt;/a&gt; would say: “I’m now thinking about the origin of the phrase ‘train of thought’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the meaning of Life? I think this is one question which has made countless souls wonder ever since we started thinking. I myself have been trying to figure out the answer to this question for quite a while now. The closest to the answer I’ve reached is: Life, or any part of it for that matter, has no absolute meaning. It only carries the meaning you attribute to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, Life is synonymous with creation. It begins with the creation of a body which houses the Life itself, and throughout our Life we try to create something or the other (the outcome need not always be a tangible object, for instance, respect or stature) We create relationships to keep us and others happy and growing. At work, we create something or the other in whatsoever form possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other main aspect of Life that provides it meaning is: giving. As humans, we are far from independent, unlike many animals who can live by themselves all their Life. We, on the other hand, wouldn’t survive a month. Since birth, we are dependent on our parents for (at least) 10 years of Life for all basic needs. Even after that, one way or the other, the dependence continues. This actually is one of the reasons we have progressed as a race over Centuries. Imagine every human baby having to figure out how to create fire (and I don’t mean using matches, I mean using stones) and hunt for food. That is the prime reason the structure of society evolved and we are living in the ‘information age’ as it happens to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third, and I consider this the most important, part of Life is Love. The times we live in, the word primarily implies romantic love. My definition happens to be much broader. It obviously includes romantic aspect of it, but the other sides to it are self love, love for your ideas, principles and values, for the work you do, for the people in your Life, for your country and your fellow humans. Now the importance of these differs to everyone depending on the priorities in one’s Life. Almost all of my posts have a mention of Love in one way or the other. That might be enough to give you a perspective on how much I love to love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently coined this phrase about myself: If something/someone can make me laugh, learn and love, the odds are high that I would like them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-note-on-motivation-&quot;&gt;A note on motivation:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two kinds of motivation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Positive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Negative (duh!) ;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While positive motivation finds its roots in love, joy and purpose, its negative counterpart arises from fear and obligation. Even though both of these might work, positive is always (and definitely) better than negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take mood, for instance. I believe that staying in a happy, cheerful and positive mood makes good things happen in your Life according to the Law Of Attraction. Even though it might be hard for you to make yourself believe it on the first day, if you want a reason as to why optimism is better, I would say, if things are not affected because of your mood (trust me, they do) even then, the situation having remained the same, the time you spent being positive was definitely more sensibly spent compared to having spent it sulking and painting doomsday scenarios. Look out, there just might be a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magical_creatures_in_Harry_Potter#Dementors&quot;&gt;dementor&lt;/a&gt; around you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patronus_Charm&quot;&gt;patronus&lt;/a&gt; is a smile, what’s yours?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long overdue</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/07/16/long-overdue/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2011 12:23:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/07/16/long-overdue/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tickle my ears and call me lazy, because that’s exactly what I’ve been the past couple of days. Not that I was not feeling guilty about not writing anything despite (trust me, I’m not lying) having 20 things in my head everyday that I could write about.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; What was stopping me? Well, that’s the mystery and even I don’t think I have an answer to that one. Maybe you should try reading the first line again :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So a lot has happened over the last few days. I’ve been super-busy with work and the Government has been its pathetic self with everything. Nothing unusual so far. I was agitated (and trust you me, I would have written a brash post about the incompetence and buffoonery that’s been going around in the Nation) on the day Mumbai had 3 blasts on Jul 13th. But as of now I’m trying to stay a bit clear of the bashing. Because for one thing, anger doesn’t yield anything. For another, the people who actually can make a big difference are, more often than not, ignorant and careless. And me swearing and boiling my blood is not that great an idea, given that I don’t have that much to spare to begin with :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1201607/&quot;&gt;Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows: Part 2&lt;/a&gt; released yesterday, and being the big fan that I am, was all the more excited especially because of it being the Finale. Luckily, I ended up going to watch it on Company outing with the interns for whom it was their last day of internship here. And most of them being HP fans themselves, it was good fun :) Before the movie, we went for their farewell lunch with almost the whole team. [I’m feeling a bit weird writing the above, just because of the reason that I’ve never maintained the blog as a journal per se]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve been having a lot of epiphanies (not new with me, but I think the frequency has increased a bit) For instance, even when every religion and book with a message tells us that Love is the most important thing on the planet, we still have so many people living with anger, pain and jealousy all the time. I wouldn’t go into the the details here. (For the philosophical souls: we can discuss this stuff at length offline)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oops, I almost missed out on the fact that I got myself a domain (Yaayy!) So check out &lt;a href=&quot;http://bhashkar.me/&quot;&gt;http://bhashkar.me/&lt;/a&gt; and let me know what you think. I’m still trying to figure out to make something good out of it. Will keep you posted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So long, till then.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life Sahi Hai!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/05/29/life-sahi-hai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2011 11:48:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/05/29/life-sahi-hai/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yup, the title happens to be same as (and not coincidentally so) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JUur2Gjyrog&quot;&gt;this song&lt;/a&gt; from ‘Pyaar Ka Punchnama’. I think this is one movie which has shown romance in a new and fresh (not to mention kinda realistic in today’s world) light.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t mean to be anything ranging from condescending to women, cynical or a love-hater here. Its just that having watched the Bollywood romantic drama for years now, and being a natural romantic, this was a perspective that caught my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May I add here that I have seen a couple of couples (heh!) going through the entire lifetime of their relationships, right from the time they came together till they eventually broke up. And people (especially guys) coming from that group would identify with this movie more. I’m not implying any side to have been wrong in the aforementioned relationships. Things happen. Besides, we all have opinions when we ourselves are neither of the party but have any kind of attachment with either of the people in there.
Other than that, this movie gave me perspective in a couple of other scenarios that I’ve seen happen to people around me. One of them was boyfriends cribbing about and foul-mouthing their girlfriends behind their backs. The other was when a friend of mine asked me “Come on, who’s not happy being single?”. My first instinct was to answer this question with a “So do people get into relationships so they can get unhappy?” but somehow I didn’t go ahead with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now as I happen to understand it, and being someone who puts in effort to understand behavioral patterns (of course, its no rocket science) we all do anything and everything for one damned reason which is- to feel happy. Correct me if I’m wrong (I know I ain’t) but that’s our aim whenever we do ANYTHING. Not just us humans, every living thing on the planet has a propensity to move into the direction of growth and joy. Relationships don’t differ either. We get into a relationship thinking that we will be happy with that person (Duh! Why else would you get into a relationship? For pain?). The funny thing is, we break up with that person for the same reason- to be Happy again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes me think- the person whose company was supposed to make us happy has now become a person we’d rather not be with/around. What changed? Us or them? Or both? Or neither, but the perspective did?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not specific to relationships. It applies to everything in our lives. We want that job because we think that the money it brings would make us happy. We want to live at some place because we think it feels good to live there. In fact, as I mentioned, this phenomenon applies to every decision in your life. That’s the reason I learned this rule and I tell everyone to follow: Whenever making a decision, especially the important ones like love or career, ask yourself a ‘Why?’ if you’re torn between choices. Judge them, not only against each other, but also on an absolute scale. There better be a damn good reason to do something. Because if you don’t have a strong enough driving force, you’d want to bail out midway. Which implies you’d be wasting your and others’ time and energy, amongst other resources.
Anyways, being a person who’s been single all his life, wait, did you ask ‘Why’? This might not be the best place to follow the golden rule I just stated. Okay, I’ll try to answer the question, if possible. Well, for one thing maybe you should ask the girls ;) As far as I am concerned, I’ve tried (and I don’t mean pretended, or make-believe) being caring, sensitive, a good listener and similar things girls supposedly want. While we’re at it, I’ll let out a little secret (okay, maybe its no longer a secret) - Girls dig bad guys. When I say this, it is limited to my own experience, of the people around me, and a few million (billion?) others. Does that imply that the odds of you getting a girl are much higher when you’re a stubborn I-don’t-give-a-fuck jerk than when you’re a romantic movie ka typical hero? I don’t know, but somewhere I believe this might be true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I heard recently from a stand-up comic, ‘Good boys get heaven, and bad boys get women’. That brings us to the ‘good boys’. What are they for? Ever known the ‘best friends’ girls have? These are the guys they reach out to when the jerk of a boyfriend hurts them and they need someone. In comes the ‘nice guy’ who consoles the girl, wipes her tears, lends her a shoulder to cry on and listens to her. Guess what happens when the girl is done crying? More often than not, she returns to the jerk of a boyfriend who wouldn’t think twice before hurting her again. No points for guessing what guys would rather want to be. Its as obvious as it gets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like I drifted off from the main topic (was there even a main topic? :P )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This movie gave me a perspective about being happy being single. I’m not making any claims about the possibility or probability of me getting, or not getting into a relationship. Its just the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=elsh3J5lJ6g&quot;&gt;enjoy the show&lt;/a&gt;‘ part I’m talking about here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a strong believer in things happening for a reason (its not all theory; I’ve had experiences in life which have strengthened my belief more than ever) I know this too (my single-hood) is for a reason. Maybe I’ll get into a relationship with a person whom I’d want to spend the rest of my life with before my parents have to worry about finding a girl to arrange-marry me (that’s the romantic &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; talking again). Maybe not. Why worry? For now, I’m gonna enjoy being single. Who knows, soon enough I might never get to be single again? ;) So its time to enjoy the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Thought: Life’s all about balance. Figure it out.]
[Idea: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6NN62PEnoMw&quot;&gt;Ishq Na Kariyo Kakke&lt;/a&gt; should be made the song of the year ;) ]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realization</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/04/18/realization/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2011 17:30:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/04/18/realization/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Squiggly. Funny word. But that’s beyond the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days I’ve been feeling a little down. For no valid reason whatsoever. I guess most of it was just because things were not happening the way I wanted them to happen, and here’s the kicker, even though I wasn’t making any conscious effort to make them happen.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And tonight as I was about to retire for bed, I realized that (clever title, huh? I know. You can stop clapping now :D ) I was not following what I preach to others all the time. Just then it hit me that my biggest worries in life are not even worth being close to be categorized as worries, besides its nothing I can’t fix. While there are people in the World who are living in lack and limitation and still are able to smile. This means I’m just not respecting life the way I should. It is THE most wonderful gift of God. Every beautiful day comes up with a whole new set of possibilities and awesomeness. Choosing to ignore all the beauty just because someone tipped your scales a little bit is SO not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love is THE most amazing thing on the planet. I don’t know why people refrain from giving love. Maybe they’re afraid of getting hurt. But giving love is not the problem, expecting in return is. But then we are all humans and expecting comes naturally to us. If only we could live by Lord Krishna’s words&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karmanye Vadhikaraste Ma Phaleshu Kadachana,
Ma Karma Phala Hetur Bhurmatey Sangostva Akarmani”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(translation: “You have a right to perform your prescribed action,but you are not entitled to the fruits of your action. Never consider yourself the cause of the results your activities, and never be associated to not doing your duty.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I guess its way too tough for people to be living this way. After all, hope (for some people, its fear) is what keeps the ball rolling for us. And I guess there’s nothing wrong about that in today’s world. But tying your happiness to someone/something external is something we must try to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know I’m good at telling others what is right, but when its time to follow it myself, I gotta keep a vigil eye on myself. I’ll leave you with one thought- “Miracles happen. You just have to be willing to see them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring it on, baby!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weekend</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/03/27/weekend/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2011 11:33:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/03/27/weekend/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I know, the title sounds lame. But this is the only time of the week that I get for myself (or so I used to think till recently, when I realized I had not been managing it well. I’m working on it, but that makes for another story).&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Right now, I’m trying to focus on this weekend which, was as un-happening from the outside as any of the 60-odd weekends in the last year, but still there was something to it I just can’t ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I’m not the one to rant or crib about my life on my blog, I just want to share some of the realizations I have been having in the last couple of days. I always try to be a student, someone who learns something from each of his experience. And I think that’s what this post is chiefly going to be about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was not feeling awesome when the weekend started. I guess I had gathered some emotional baggage, most of it, now that I can see, was totally needless and pointless. And I think I’ve been playing an uber-emotional fellow for so long that I had led myself into believing that’s who I am. And after that things just happened the way my mindset was, and I spiraled myself into some emotional complications which, as I priorly indicated, were totally unneeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friends, as they say, are precious. And this was no different a case. I was brought back to my senses thanks to the counselling sessions (lets call them that) by a very dear friend of mine. In addition, to feel good I started watching ‘[Scrubs]’ and that did it. Two days later, I’m my jumpy self again. And I guess there always are lessons to be learnt. So from this story I learnt a little bit of what relationships are REALLY about, and what makes them work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Can’t think of what to add.. maybe later :) ]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sync your Nokia contacts with GMail contacts</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/31/sync-your-nokia-contacts-with-gmail-contacts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 13:43:20 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/31/sync-your-nokia-contacts-with-gmail-contacts/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://rockerhome.files.wordpress.com/2011/01/gmail-app-mobile.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;Nokia GMail sync&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi fellas. So I have this Nokia S60 phone (5233) which, sadly, does not have support for Mail for Exchange ActiveSync. And that is the reason I started looking for alternatives to backup and sync my contacts and calendar.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; An option that can serve the backup purpose is &lt;a href=&quot;http://ovi.com/&quot;&gt;Nokia Ovi&lt;/a&gt; but that is limited to a backup and restore functionality and does not support any syncing with other services AFAIK, which didn’t help my purpose. So I started searching for other alternatives. Now, I don’t know whether any paid solutions work (assuming they exist) but yours truly was not looking for those. After running some queries on Google, I landed on some interesting solutions. And the one that worked for me, I’m sharing here: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to Settings » Connectivity » Data transfer » Sync&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select ‘Options’ » ‘New sync profile’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A profile wizard will start, and would ask for a profile name. Just give a unique name such as ‘GMail sync’ and hit ‘Next’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now it would prompt you for a server version. Choose ‘1.2’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next, choose what you want to sync. In our case, it will just be ‘Contacts’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now, the name of the Contacts database. Enter exactly ‘Contacts’ (without the quotes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For Data bearer, choose ‘Internet’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host address next. Enter the URL ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://m.google.com/syncml&quot;&gt;https://m.google.com/syncml&lt;/a&gt;‘&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Server ID will be ‘Google’ &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Port, if it prompts you for, would be ‘443’ &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now for the login credentials: Username and Password. Just enter your Google account username and password.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Okay, we are good to go. Now choose ‘Save profile’. It will prompt you for whether this should be the active profile. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose ‘Yes’. Now all you need to do is go to ‘Options’ » ‘Synchronize’. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once synchronization is complete, all your GMail contacts will be in sync with your phone contacts and vice-versa. Oh, and did I mention that includes the pics that people have set as their Google profile pic? Cool, huh? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you can get push mail for your phone using Nokia Mail service, for which you might need to update your phone software. I updated my phone recently and is currently running V 21.1.102 dated 17-09-2010. Works beautifully for me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default Email app has inbuilt templates for GMail, Yahoo! mail, Hotmail, Rediffmail etc. And an option ‘others’, although I think very few would need to go there. I’m hoping it helps! :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take care. I will be back. Till then…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Its about time</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/29/its-about-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2011 06:22:11 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/29/its-about-time/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Okay people! I promised I would find a worthy use for this blog of mine, since anyways I’m not able to focus on all the blogs I have created over time, so I figured lets make the best possible out of what I got. And I came up with this: technology is one thing I tinker with almost all the time and I guess it would be a good idea to share some of the things I have stumbled upon so that more people can have fun with them! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said it. Its gonna be a tech-blog from now on. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Happy Republic Day</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/25/happy-republic-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2011 17:12:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/25/happy-republic-day/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…and along comes the season of patriotism. It is that time of the year when we all forward “Happy Republic Day” and “proud to be an Indian” kind of text messages and emails. The time when we tag each other in “patriotic” images.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; And come 27th Jan, we return to being ourselves till the 15th August, where this process is repeated. Wait, is that not what it was all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Constitution of India&lt;/em&gt; defines us as a “&lt;strong&gt;Secular Socialist Sovereign Democratic Republic&lt;/strong&gt;“. But the fact of the matter is, the only secularism that we see is used to protect the minorities’ interests, as long as it fetches votes. The individual might have broken the law, but the real point that is made is that since he is a minority, these actions are being taken against him. Again, I’m not in favor of any kind of terrorism, be it region-based (think: MNS or Telangana for that matter) or religion-based (I’m equally against the Hindu terrorist groups as I’m against the others). I’m totally up for &lt;strong&gt;social&lt;/strong&gt; and economic equality, but is that what we see around us? We might be &lt;strong&gt;sovereign&lt;/strong&gt; in theory, but I have my doubts about the external powers influencing our country’s decision making. &lt;strong&gt;Democracy&lt;/strong&gt; is at best a de-mock-racy. Of the people, by the people.. and I can’t stop laughing- for the people? I guess the “people” here are the ones sitting on thrones. We removed 500 kings and created 50000 of them. We indeed are &lt;strong&gt;republic&lt;/strong&gt; in the sense that the Head of State is not a monarch. And why? Because the Head of State is a puppet in the hands of the real monarch. Definition of &lt;strong&gt;monarchy&lt;/strong&gt;: an autocracy governed by a monarch who usually inherits the authority. Sounds familiar?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel sad when I remember the immortal lines “&lt;em&gt;Shaheedon ki chita par lagengey har baras mele.. Vatan par marne walo ka yahi baaki nishaan hoga&lt;/em&gt;“. Today nobody cares to remember the people who gave their lives to ensure that coming generations can breathe in a free country. Gone are the days when people like Swami Vivekananda, Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose and Shaheed Bhagat Singh used to be the youth icons. Today, the only people who are respected are the ones who have either money or power (well, one brings the other). And don’t even get me started on youth. We have been so blinded by the wave of consumerism that we tend to feel proud in purchasing sweet soda water and thinking “This is cool. I’m doing a very youthful thing”. We remember Valentine’s Day, but seldom even notice the birthdays of the great people who lived and died for the country. (Just so we’re clear, I have nothing against Love. It is a very beautiful thing. In fact, I believe Love to be the greatest power in the Universe. Refer ‘&lt;em&gt;The Power&lt;/em&gt;‘ - Rhonda Byrne). The so-called “icons” and “idols” are buffoons at best, leaving apart a few exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have become used to entertainment. I’m not referring to movies or music or dance or any other kind of recreational activity, for that matter. I am talking about how the Media is offering us, what I can call in the most delicate terms, crap. We watch it with a similar interest as we would have had we been watching a soap opera. And the best part is, our interest/concern for the subject fades away in the same amount of time it would, had it been fiction. But what is sad is that its not fiction. Not even close. Its our lives. Pardon me for being dramatic, but I would go ahead and compare it to the situation of lighting your own house on fire just for the fun of watching something burn, or to slit own wrists for the fun of watching red color splatter all over. How? Maybe its not that easy to see it when you think of yourself as an individual, an independent entity. But what we can’t and shouldn’t forget is that we are not independent. We, as humans, were born dependent. And we will always be. That is the reason the structure of society evolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry for drifting away from the point. I tend to get carried away when I write. The point is, we need to put some thought (and actions) into it. I don’t need to reiterate over all that needs to be fixed. We are a fast growing economy, indeed. We have the best brains on the planet. And we have the second-largest population on the planet, and the largest population of youth (which, I’m citing here as a positive point. Why? Think what would happen if all the human resources can be managed and put to good use in the right way). We are blessed and gifted. But then, why aren’t we innovating new technologies and products? Why aren’t our sportspersons bagging the most awards? Despite Indians being the largest portion of NASA, Microsoft and the likes, why those miracles are not being done back at home? (I agree that they are technically far ahead of us. But what is stopping us from a speedy recovery?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in a 21st Century India where on one hand women are equal to men in all aspects, yet a girl child is murdered before birth. The number of &lt;strong&gt;reported&lt;/strong&gt; rape cases averages to around 15 a day (stats: 2009). Discrimination, eve-teasing and sexual harassment are the things which the women of our Nation have to face regularly. If someone marries against their folks’ will, they are murdered. In the country of “Atithi Devo Bhava”, tourists are raped and robbed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I very strongly feel that the acts which involve taking the people’s money and betraying their trust by not proactively performing the duties should be treated as Sedition - an act against the Nation. And the ones performing those should be penalized severely. These, by the way, include incompetence and corruption, for starters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we have a new scam every couple of years (last year topped it all) that amounts to hundreds of billions and the people who are involved continue to roam freely, not to mention with added money and fame? Why don’t people like A. Raja, Suresh Kalmadi, Mayawati etc. get the treatment they deserve? Why Indians are so intent on breaking the Nation into pieces in as many ways as possible. Be it religion, caste, region, state; its a “you name it, we have it” situation. Why is the state of law and order so bad in some places that people prefer to choose the terror groups instead of the government? Why are the prices soaring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite a bag of questions, but I guess this is the simplest way to vent out all that has been in my head. And this list is far from complete. We’re just getting started.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Get this!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/05/get-this/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2011 09:11:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2011/01/05/get-this/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A Poem &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many many years ago&lt;br/&gt;
when I was twenty three,&lt;br/&gt;
I got married to a widow&lt;br/&gt;
Who was pretty as could be.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This widow had a grown-up daughter&lt;br/&gt;
Who had hair of red.&lt;br/&gt;
My father fell in love with her,&lt;br/&gt;
And soon the two were wed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made my dad my son-in-law&lt;br/&gt;
And changed my very life.&lt;br/&gt;
My daughter was my mother,&lt;br/&gt;
For she was my father’s wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To complicate the matters worse,&lt;br/&gt;
Although it brought me joy,&lt;br/&gt;
I soon became the father&lt;br/&gt;
Of a bouncing baby boy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My little baby then became&lt;br/&gt;
A brother-in-law to dad.&lt;br/&gt;
And so became my uncle,&lt;br/&gt;
Though it made me very sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For if he was my uncle,&lt;br/&gt;
Then that also made him brother&lt;br/&gt;
To the widow’s grown-up daughter&lt;br/&gt;
Who, of course, was my step-mother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Father’s wife then had a son,&lt;br/&gt;
Who kept them on the run.&lt;br/&gt;
And he became my grandson,&lt;br/&gt;
For he was my daughter’s son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife is now my mother’s mother&lt;br/&gt;
And it makes me blue.&lt;br/&gt;
Because, although she is my wife,&lt;br/&gt;
She’s my grandmother too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If my wife is my grandmother,&lt;br/&gt;
Then I am her grandchild.&lt;br/&gt;
And every time I think of it,&lt;br/&gt;
It simply drives me wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now I have become&lt;br/&gt;
The strangest case you ever saw.&lt;br/&gt;
As the husband of my grandmother,&lt;br/&gt;
I am my own grandpa!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[source unknown]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social? Really?</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/12/04/social-really/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 16:05:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/12/04/social-really/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Disclaimer: This article is in no way written with any prejudices towards social networking and internet socializing. Its purpose is to point out that virtual ‘social’ world is shadowing the real ‘social’ world. That doesn’t sound amusing to me, especially going forward.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is an amazing journey, inter-spaced with gifts and lessons. Gifts are what we see as the ‘good’ things happening to us, while lessons are their ‘bad’ counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, it feels as if I’m taking a course. The course involves understanding humans- their behavior, thought patterns, belief systems etc. And in the last year I have been a student of human behavior, I have learnt things about relationships (and not just romantic ones), about people feeling good/bad or happy/sad, about their reactions to situations. (I apologize if I sound like an alien here :P )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning I read an article by Simon Sinek (you can read it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.askmen.com/money/career_400/431_true-friendship-simon-sinek.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) about friendship. This made me think for the umpteenth time. Facebook tells me I have almost 300 (and counting) friends, Orkut says the number is closer to 225. According to twitter, I have almost 100 “followers” (I never know I was a leader ;) ) I’m pretty sure other sites will have similar stats to show me, but when I reflect and ponder about how many of these people belong to the category whom I’d like to hang out with for a whole day, or whom I would call when I’m feeling distressed, or want to open my heart to; these numbers lose their meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are indeed ‘connected’ and within a very easy reach of everyone in today’s “networked” world. But “do we have the warmth and closeness in friendships and relationships?” is the big question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, being a person who hates stereotyping and everyone with a stereotyped mentality (am I committing the same felony here? Keep guessing ;) ) but it seems to me that despite having a never-before myriad of connecting technologies and devices, we kind of are not close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real ‘groups’, ‘communities’ and ‘networks’ don’t exist on social networking sites, they thrive in the feeling of togetherness and unity, and in the joy of sharing and caring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’m more emotional than a ‘practical’ person (as some refer to the kaam-nikalo-chalte-bano breed of people), but my question is, am I the only one out there?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In PyCon 2010</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/09/26/in-pycon-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2010 03:11:55 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/09/26/in-pycon-2010/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[This post has been imported from my blogspot blog, where it looked a bit misplaced to me considering the fact that I post my ramblings there. Besides, this does the job of first tech-post that I needed to write. For sanity’s sake, I have kept the same publishing date as on the original post. A few enhancements have been made to the post. Have fun.]&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve just got back from InPyCon’2010.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was my first time being to a Technology Convention, and not too bad an experience. Although I had expected it to be at a different level thinking that this is The PyCon (meaning the International version) but being what it actually was, it was fine, I must say. Needless to say, being the love of my life; graphics, animation and UX if brought together, I don’t think  there is anything more interesting and intriguing to me as a technologist. And that was precisely what happened at InPyCon. (Actually, this was the only interesting part of the conention I actually enjoyed) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two things which I came across today which have got me fantasizing (don’t get the wrong idea ;) ) and kept me awake at 3 in the morning (this can explain how excited I am!) writing this blog post. :) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve uploaded this video to make some sense out of all the gibberish I’ve been shooting till now (think: low cost VR and touch panels :) ). If you find it interesting, you might also want to visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://asimmittal.net/&quot;&gt;the presenter’s site&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also taking the liberty to include the link to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.johnnylee.net/&quot;&gt;the source&lt;/a&gt; of his inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;video-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/hmISFEQctuQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other presentation that I really had fun at was the one about 3D Game development in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blender.org/&quot;&gt;Blender&lt;/a&gt; which is a Python based gaming-engine-cum-IDE. Think about it. Free. Open source. And allows you to build 3D games. And did I mention that you don’t need to write code for that? That’s right, my friend! I’m definitely gonna get my hands dirty with it. (Takes a while to get acquainted with the tools, I hear, but nevertheless, worth a shot all the same!) :) Enjoy!! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post comments. I, in the meanwhile, will try to get things moving in the direction where I can put all this knowledge to good use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ciao for now!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Writing from Pune</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/08/13/writing-from-pune/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13  Aug 2010 12:27:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/08/13/writing-from-pune/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday finally I got to do what I had been meaning to do for quite a while now - visit Pune. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With so many of college people out there and almost no one having time to travel between places (atleast that’s what they tried to imply) ;) I figured I’d do the needful if I had to meet those busy souls.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon reaching here today morning after a 19-hour journey, it was pleasant and awesome meeting Nikunj (abhi tak I have met only him :) ), after more than a year, as it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as it wasn’t an off for him, he left for work; leaving me all by myself, with his laptop. While I tried indulging in watching various TV series and movies (trust me, I did :P ), I somehow just ended up falling asleep only to be waken up past 1600 hrs to wait for him to be back, which, I’m hoping happens ASAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it wasn’t much of content to be posted on my blog… but then this day made me re-realize something. The very fact that we all have been knowing for eternity by now.. that humans are strictly social beings… and that explains why one of the toughest punishments of all times used to (and probably still continues to) be solitary confinement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And one more thing: books and music are two of the best buddies in loneliness. Trust me. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ciao for now!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Being in Twenties</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/07/28/being-in-twenties/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jul 2010 10:35:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/07/28/being-in-twenties/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here I would like to make it clear upfront that this is not a piece written by me. A friend mailed it to me and I found it worth reading, and so considered the best to share it with the World. The copy-paste begins:&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is when you stop going along with the crowd and start realizing that there are many things about yourself that you didn’t know and may not like. You start feeling insecure and wonder where you will be in a year or two, but then get scared because you barely know where you are now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You start realizing that people are selfish and that, maybe, those friends that you thought you were so close to aren’t exactly the greatest people you have ever met, and the people you have lost touch with are some of the most important ones. What you don’t recognize is that they are realizing that too, and aren’t really cold, catty, mean or insincere, but that they are as confused as you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You look at your job… and it is not even close to what you thought you would be doing, or maybe you are looking for a job and realizing that you are going to have to start at the bottom and that scares you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your opinions have gotten stronger. You see what others are doing and find yourself judging more than usual because suddenly you realize that you have certain boundaries in your life and are constantly adding things to your list of what is acceptable and what isn’t. One minute, you are insecure and then the next, secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You laugh and cry with the greatest force of your life. You feel alone and scared and confused. Suddenly, change is the enemy and you try and cling on to the past with dear life, but soon realize that the past is drifting further and further away, and there is nothing to do but stay where you are or move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get your heart broken and wonder how someone you loved could do such damage to you. Or you lie in bed and wonder why you can’t meet anyone decent enough that you want to get to know better. Or maybe you love someone but love someone else too and cannot figure out why you’re doing this because you know that you aren’t a bad person. One night stands and random hook ups start to look cheap. You want to settle down for good because now all of a sudden that becomes top priority. Getting wasted and acting like an idiot starts to look pathetic.You begin to think a companion for life is better than a hundred in the shack and for once you would not mind standing tall for that special someone which otherwise you had never thought of until now.You go through the same emotions and questions over and over, and talk with your friends about the same topics because you cannot seem to make a decision. You worry about loans, money, the future and making a life for yourself… and while winning the race would be great, right now you’d just like to be a contender!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you may not realize is that every one reading this relates to it. We are in our best of times and our worst of times, trying as hard as we can to figure this whole thing out. Send this to your twenty-something friends… maybe it will help someone feel like they aren’t alone in their state of confusion…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We call it the “Quarter-life Crisis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FATE DETERMINES WHO COMES INTO OUR LIVES…..HEART DETERMINES WHO STAYS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the beautiful journey that life is. Love and light to all!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>You can befool all the people, all the time...</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/07/14/you-can-befool-all-the-people-all-the-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2010 14:39:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/07/14/you-can-befool-all-the-people-all-the-time/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…as Apple does it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong here. I’m no Microsoft-phile, nor am I an Apple hater, or even an open-source-rer for that matter. Honestly speaking, I find it really hard to choose one over the other in the real World where we all live, and perfection is far from a possibility.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; I revere Steve Jobs for the miraculous person that he is, for the vision he has, the products he creates… et al. And honestly speaking, it is very much possible that we all would still have ugly hardware for our devices (not that every other company is making them ugly, its just that Steve was the pioneer in realizing the Consumer Appliance aspect of computers as we see them today) had it not been for him. And the ‘just works’ and ‘plug-n-play’ was implemented by Apple way before any other company could come even close in competition. And even today, the implementation by Apple is as smooth and seamless as it gets. Not to mention the effect its products have on people. Once you start using an Apple product, you’ll fall in love with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there always has been this aspect of Apple that limits the freedom, in many ways. Apple always has kept some or the other form of restriction regarding its products. Be it hardware or software (again, I’m not denying the panache Apple’s products have. It is probably the only company on the planet which can make people wait outside its stores for hours in advance for its latest product launch, and pretty much the only company which can get a pre-order of a million of its latest cellphone model, even before people actually get to see it; and the best part is, those people would include both, those who’ve experienced and own Apple’s products, as well as those who’re first-timers and are driven by the hype and the branding et al), Apple has got restrictions all over the place. Jobs, the Perfectionist Extraordinaire that he is, has his own way of putting it. He doesn’t want the User Experience to get spoiled or hampered in any way because some piece of ‘ugly’ code was running on his product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I recently was reading, Apple was said to be an exception, apart from around a million ways in which it already has been touted as one, in the way its ‘closed innovation’ is driving open innovation. I personally feel that this is an increasingly open world, and it would be in the best of interest of all if Apple has more relaxed attitude towards open-source. That reminds me, check this out: this is one of the most famous advertising campaigns in history, the Apple &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OYecfV3ubP8&quot;&gt;1984 superbowl ad&lt;/a&gt;, that revolutionized the impact the company had on the World. Closely listen to what the voice in the background-portrayed to be a dictator in technology world-has to say. Funny thing, today you can make similar sense out of Steve’s words. Has Apple forgotten what it stood for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel kind of stuck here. If I need to make a choice between open-source and Apple, which one would I make? No comments!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bingo!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/07/09/bingo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2010 17:54:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/07/09/bingo/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…and here we go! My blog can finally be read on mobile (that is, in a perfectly mobile-readable format) as easily as it can get. Thanks to MobStac B! :P :P&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay.. I’m not here doing the advertisement of some product. This is something which I have been a part of, and has been what I’ve been working on in the past few months, and to see it come to life (read: going Live) is one ecstatic experience. I’m lovin’ it, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shall add more later… Ciao for now! :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What do you know...</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/04/25/what-do-you-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2010 17:05:55 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/04/25/what-do-you-know/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Well.. call this post a placeholder or dummy text or wateva you want… its here because I’ m finding myself too busy to come up with something substantial, as of now! Later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Housekeeping</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/04/22/housekeeping/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2010 09:59:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/04/22/housekeeping/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey fellas! That’s rite… We’ve moved. Now we’re found chiefly on our homeblog… presence at other locations may or maynot be relevant. It’d be good if you check beforehand.. :P&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
After going thru an export-import cycle; I finally managed to get my blog posts back to home… Then the tweaking of look-and-feel began and, I guess this is the outcome… for now!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I got another awesome book from office.. God I so am in love with the Usability book that I already had… and now this frickin compendium of JS from O’Reilly… No wonder I love reading! :P
A bit of technical stuff: I apologize to all the frameworks which, I wrongly used to think, were no more than something that eases your work; which, for me, implicitly implied that only “aalsi” category of people would be using them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have been using a few of the really great ones at work, I have come to realize that it is not only about the ease; it is about standardization, and super-efficient code-reuse… which, by the way, are key factors in today’s application development scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My latest addiction: Two And A Half Men… n its hilarious, I tell ya!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With these changes and a couple of realizations regarding social networking and related phenomena, I guess I will be frequenting my blog and socializing sites more often than I previously used to..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there’s too much randomness in the text, pardon me for that. Word of the day: Entropy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ciao..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What's happening</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2010/03/27/what-s-happening/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Mar 2010 14:51:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2010/03/27/what-s-happening/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wow, people… I really apologize for my regular procrastination in updating the blog… but this time, all I can promise is that I will try to be back as soon as possible, without giving you any false hopes on when that will be…&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have went through a lot of stuff in the meanwhile… the story in short after the last post has been thus: I moved back to my hometown, swine flu was on a rampage at that time, the death toll had really mounted high.. Celebrated my birthday and Diwali @ home while prepping up for the CAT n other management entrance exams… moved to Delhi at the end of November to give all those tests which happened to be in the month of December for the most part… It was then that I discovered The Secret.. thanks a lot Tapas bhai.. I can never thank you enough for this…but then, as they say, everything happens for a reason. I’m saying this because my very good friend and colleague Nikunj recommended The Secret to me when we were still at college. Do you know the best part? I got the movie, gave it to hime and not once tried to watch it, despite his repeated prodding me to do so…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My saga continues.. Then I gave the CATs and moved to Bengaluru.. felt like it was calling me and this time was THE TIME when I would land on something. Not just something for the sake of it, but something solid and substantial. Something that can make me feel like I’m actually doing what I love to do, in a manner I wish to do it… The Secret was in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached Bengaluru and stayed with my friends who were already working with Accenture by the time. And I started looking for a job. Fast-Forward two months, and I am working with MobileMotion Technologies, a startup that creates stuff that makes mobile internet experience easier, faster and hassle-free. And did I tell you that I love my job, the stuff I work on and my coworkers are simply amazing guys… each of them a Rockstar in his field, I thank Lord so much for giving me the perfect company and working environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve moved in with my college senior, Shivansh, who’s also one of my colleagues at MM… the new place is closer to the office and, needless to say, is WAY much better than the PG I used to live in..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life’s going great. Thank you friends. Thank you Rhonda. Thank you God.
As they’d say at McD’s- I’m lovin’ it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s my story guys! You say what’s up at your end?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Everything on sale!</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2009/08/10/everything-on-sale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10  Aug 2009 04:14:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2009/08/10/everything-on-sale/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It makes me wonder- have the companies started producing low-grade products in ridiculous quantities that they HAVE TO sell at low prices to get rid of them; or have they been trying to lure the class of people who could not previously afford their products and make them addicted; or its all just a farce, and the GREATER GOOD is worked out by affixing a tag displaying the price at least four times the actual (and I mean selling) price of the product, and providing a 40% DISCOUNT on it. Get robbed. Everyone’s invited!&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We might have been accustomed to this idea as we’ve been seeing these strategies (how can we forget the kid-luring stuff that they give FREE with their products) in action since forever. But there is still a class of people, such as those who’ve recently migrated from towns to metros and the likes, who get thrilled at the thought of making such a good bargain, and thus get carried away. As for the Gen-Now, the metro-kid since birth, and having got ample opportunities to visit the innumerable outlets around them, they go for  stuff only if they feel like it, unless they’ve turned into shopaholics. For the pampered lot, it doesn’t matter to them whether the price is 20% or 200%, they’d buy it if they have to. What sucks is that companies are luring people to consumerism, at its dirtiest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the question- “What’s wrong about it?” does indeed have an answer. Just look at how small kids are being used to add to the appeal of products varying from toys to cars, and you’d know what am I talking about. I wonder if they show healthy programs for kids for durations equivalent to time each day spent showing kids trying to sell stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And celebs, I just do not have words for them. Nobody knows whether they themselves heard of the product they’re promoting till they’ve started promoting it. And mind it! They’re still just talking about the stuff, not using it. Just by holding a pack of products and speaking lines about it, they’re laughing their way to the bank. And the vicious circle of consumerism sucks the consumer into the black hole with no escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don’t even get me started on status symbols. Gosh! Its not just grown-up stuff anymore. I mean, kids HAVE TO own stuff such as a Playstation or an iPod even before they learn their remainder theorems.  And why? Just because some friend of theirs, another pampered kid from next block owns it. And what about all the extra sums that the parents have to cough up in fulfilling the kids’ demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a grown-up level, the phenomenon acquires a deadly and dirty face. Be it owning a big car, branded jewelry or living in a posh locality, grown-ups exhibit a kiddish behavior regarding these issues and sometimes value these petty things more then their lives, families, relationships…
Consumerism has indeed taken its toll on us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And who’s to blame, and be benefited by it all, is not something I need to tell you. Right?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unnamed Poem</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2009/08/05/the-unnamed-poem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05  Aug 2009 13:10:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2009/08/05/the-unnamed-poem/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi Fellas! Following is something that I came up with during the time my precious YearBook was under construction. Although I couldn’t make it very complete or appealing, yet thought it best to post it here, so it can be read by you:&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This world around me,&lt;br /&gt;
its fun 2 b in.&lt;br /&gt;
As i fight 2 stay awake,&lt;br /&gt;
midst of my day,&lt;br /&gt;
rough as it is,&lt;br /&gt;
ain’t no piece of cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Define love- the toughest question of all times,&lt;br /&gt;
comes to haunt me. Sick as it is,&lt;br /&gt;
this world is love-stricken.&lt;br /&gt;
The existence of a new paradigm&lt;br /&gt;
of operability, adds a flavor&lt;br /&gt;
of tranquility&lt;br /&gt;
which is why love is referred to as&lt;br /&gt;
God in some places n the inexplicable&lt;br /&gt;
in others.&lt;br /&gt;
But one thing that persists&lt;br /&gt;
is the purity n sanctity&lt;br /&gt;
that true love holds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Also, following is a lovely song featured in Scrubs episode 201. The song is called ‘Overkill’ and features Colin Hay in the video. You can also see the video on YouTube &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6JPzi1Su9T4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t get to sleep&lt;br /&gt;
I think about the implications&lt;br /&gt;
Of diving in too deep&lt;br /&gt;
And possibly the complications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially at night&lt;br /&gt;
I worry over situations&lt;br /&gt;
I know I’ll be alright&lt;br /&gt;
Perhaps it’s just imagination&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day after day it reappears&lt;br /&gt;
Night after night my heartbeat shows the fear&lt;br /&gt;
Ghosts appear and fade away&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alone between the sheets&lt;br /&gt;
Only brings exasperation&lt;br /&gt;
It’s time to walk the streets&lt;br /&gt;
Smell the desperation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least there’s pretty lights&lt;br /&gt;
And though there’s little variation&lt;br /&gt;
It nullifies the night from overkill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day after day it reappears&lt;br /&gt;
Night after night my heartbeat shows the fear&lt;br /&gt;
Ghosts appear and fade away&lt;br /&gt;
Come back another day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t get to sleep&lt;br /&gt;
I think about the implications&lt;br /&gt;
Of diving in too deep&lt;br /&gt;
And possibly the complications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially at night&lt;br /&gt;
I worry over situations&lt;br /&gt;
I know I’ll be alright&lt;br /&gt;
It’s just overkill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day after day it reappears&lt;br /&gt;
Night after night my heartbeat shows the fear&lt;br /&gt;
Ghosts appear and fade away&lt;br /&gt;
Ghosts appear and fade away&lt;br /&gt;
Ghosts appear and fade away.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking back...</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2008/12/19/looking-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2008 12:46:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2008/12/19/looking-back/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;And how much I wish to be faring in the ‘Alumni Speaks’ section in some edition of KNOL, or MUCUR (only if it had one, for that matter) after we finish college. Lookin back…. Sweet aint it?&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; The ride through the time… remembering everything now seems a breeze… but there’ve been mightier times… remember when the POLICE came to make the encroached boundary turn to dust…. Lol… life was so much (jus can’t find the adjective)… or times amongst ourselves… having a Tappi night-out to IIT for THOMSO… things just couldn’t get better, atleast in this gloomy city but things actually are that MAST… all those booze sessions (just 2 be clear I never got that thing down my throat) on-the-rocks in hostels n the coming-up vomit (Yuck that sucks!) but yeah to admit it was all a part of life…. I’ve seen the life of both, that of a ground floor boy, easily the most studious lobby of hostel as well as that of a next-to-top floor guy belonging to the most BAKAR wing of the hostel… yeah enjoyment comes to thou whether or not you seek it there… lovely ;-)…. Momo-wallah out there… not to 4get Royal k parathe (how innumerable times have they proved time n again to be life savers)… then Roorkee trips… Vikram, Bus, Truck, Canter, lift in a car, you name it… almost all of the possible terrestrial modes of transportation have been utilized in making these trips (how much would day-scholars would miss it!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things don’t end here… remember how much all of us liked to curse THE DICTATOR?? Not content with makin our life a prison, he could easily go ahead to makin it a living hell had he got his wish… mmmph!!! N same was the story wid the faculty… some of them really cool, other not that much… but wat the hell, the cursing was an inseperable part of their schedule as well…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the café, the most happenin point of the college (Las Vegas? Naaaah!)… all of the couples come there to pass their evenings.. Have seen the café as crowded as hell (orientation day or the Zion), n seen it totally deserted (exams days)… innumerable memories there as well… it was easily the dwelling for the committee ppl conducting the fest there… the commotion there…enjoyin the times when the rains struck hard on the café roof, we were in thr… not cosy but definitely, sipping tea in such a weather gives a us a freewheeling attitude, atleast for a matter of seconds.. after all, the prison still is THERE… n of us all inmates, (not talkin of the studious type, those who dare not lift their eyes off the books just for the fear of dropping their grades, or specs, if you might)… humans deserve freedom dude, give it to them…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To, Knol</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2008/11/30/to-knol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2008 09:36:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2008/11/30/to-knol/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You guys might be wondering what’s with this surge of enlightenment amongst the final years that’s been keeping them on their toes working so hard to bring out a mag such as this. Well, the excitement of being a creator, that’s known to all of us, constitutes one of the prime reasons for the same. Yet it’s not all, far from being the heart and soul of the matter.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, as the legend goes, our dearest friend Nix (this being the Linux version for Nikunj; derived from good old buddy Tux, the Linux mascot penguin – courtesy me, although his pet names like ‘Niks’ (mark the difference!)or ‘Lambu’ already were in existence) came up with the stupendously superb idea of publishing an e-mag that’d carry the informal as well as formal stuff pertaining to college happenings and activities. An e-mag was a good choice due to many a reasons quoting all of which is neither necessary nor required here. A few of the many would be the easy distribution, the almost priceless (either way!) creation and best of all- on-the-fly readability. That’s really brilliant, my friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, being an avid reader (interested in the details? Check out my Orkut profile) I considered penning something down for the mag, first edition, but sadly, lazy as I am, could do little to bring my thoughts into action. Nothing new in it, I’ve achieved flawless perfection in postponing things with official deadlines to the last possible extent. But the summary of it all was that I was pretty much unable to be able to be featuring my name in the volume 1 of KNOL (MUCUR’s been missing me so much for all the same reasons all this while). I finally figured out that it’s time to be up-n-running or it’s a now-or-never situation for me. And this is the first write-up that I’m composing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I couldn’t figure out what to write, so here I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congrats to the KNOL team for all the good work. And hey guys, could u try making it more informal? After all, it’s OUR mag pals. And to Nikunj, hats off dude. Keep up the good work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take care. Hoping to be able to extract all the more fun from the upcoming issues, yours truly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new era</title>
      <link>http://bhashkar.me/2008/11/30/a-new-era/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2008 08:40:00 +0630</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://bhashkar.me/2008/11/30/a-new-era/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;First of all, I’d very much like to thank Nix for reawakening my interest in writing. Had it not been for his recommendation, I wud never’ve started wid this stuff. Thanks mate.&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, its a matter of yesterday (literally so) that our Jawans have eliminated all the terrorists and freed the hostages held captive in the luxury hotels of Mumbai, namely, the Taj, Trident and Oberoi. After a continuous firing of 50 or more hours and loss of lives of more than 100 people (the casualties includes foreign tourists, VVIPs and not to forget, the Chief and other Jawans of the ATS - the Anti-Terrorist Squad, were they finally able to free the hostages. There were bombs planted in the hotels, to add to the destruction. Parts of hotels were destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attack is finally over, but it left scars on the face of Mumbai, and India. The citizens are not secure in the elite hotels, forget about the general public living in their crowded colonies and those in the markets and crowded spaces such as railway stations, metros, buses, et seq. The transportation is insecure, the hotels are insecure and so are our homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This happens just days after Mumbai suffered another attack - that of the Mumbaikars. The Maharashtra Navnirman Sena (MNS) and Raj Thackray happen to be causing enough harm to the secular, socialist, republic image of our Nation. The Maharashtrians arebeing mislead by these demagogues who are making all the profit out of befooling and murdering innocent people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might sound a bit too harsh, but India, in my opinion, needs a Dictator for the time-being. The person should be someone who can think about National interests, sidelining his personal interests. Then only wud it be possible to bring about a true change in the face and the fate of the Nation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>